the science and practice of enhancing
human performance for sport play and
life Welcome to
perform I'm Dr Andy Galpin I'm a
professor and scientist and the
executive director of the human
performance center at Parker University
in today's conversation I'm going to be
talking to my friend Dr Tommy wood Tommy
has an undergraduate degree in
Biochemistry from Cambridge University a
medical degree from Oxford as well as a
PhD in physiology and Neuroscience Tommy
is now running his neonatal Neuroscience
Lab at the University of Washington in
addition to all that he is a well-versed
rower and strongman and has worked with
athletes across every sport and in
particular more recently focusing a lot
on Formula 1 drivers and I say all this
to help you understand that Tommy's
ability to run back and forth between
physiology and Science and application
in human performance is really
unparalleled in the area of brain health
and cognitive function so in our
discussions today we talk a lot about
those areas we talk about how to enhance
understand identify short-term cognitive
performance what that even means what
that looks like from an exercise and
supplementation and Technology
perspective and then we talk about how
that looks in the long term so how do we
prevent and even deter or eliminate
things like dementia and brain aging and
Tommy over the course of our discussion
will bring up at least five points that
I feel like are quite counterintuitive
or in other words are going to surprise
or potentially even aggravate some folks
out there the reality of it is I don't
think a lot of us truly understand the
current state of the literature on both
short and long-term cognitive function
and Tommy does a wonderful job in this
conversation of bringing that to the
Forefront so we really are more
understanding of of what the literature
says and how that transfers into
practical application another thing I
think worth mentioning here that we get
into that I get asked about all the time
is how things like exercise have a
causal effect on brain health of course
there's a correlation between you know
strong muscle and physical performance
and how well you age but how is it
directly impacting and how is that I
causal if it is at all Tomley
wonderfully walks us through all that in
a way that I think everyone can
comprehend and get a great grasp on so
with all that in mind I hope you
thoroughly enjoyed this conversation
today with Dr Tommy wood Dr Tommy wood
welcome to perform thanks so much for
having me I'm really excited to be here
with you there's a lot of things I want
to get into today um things that you and
I have chatted about before but mostly
things that I actually don't know the
answer to um hopefully I can pry some
information out of you about enhancing
brain performance uh things that we can
do now in the short term as well as
long-term brain health um but I think
before we can get to that for my own
personal sake I know I say some of these
things wrong so I'm hoping you can kind
of fix this but maybe it would be best
for us to just start off with what is
cognitive performance how do you define
that how should we think about it and
what are the aspects of cognitive
performance I think one issue that's
come up a lot recently in this in this
field is that some of these things are
actually very hard to Define so when we
think about cognitive function more
broadly the way that we've traditionally
thought about it is how do you perform
on some standard cognitive test like an
IQ test um and then there are tests for
a whole bunch of other functions like
executive function or response
inhibition right trying to uh suppress
the desire to to make a response uh
which is an important part of planning
and the prefrontal cortex is plays a big
role there um also testing working
memory and all these other things that
we might um or you our ability to learn
and remember in short periods of
time and that's kind of what we've had
because that's what we've got we have
standardized tests we know how you score
compared to other people we think we
understand which parts of the brain are
involved in those functions but the the
real problem is that while they do
relate slightly to the different
functions you and I would want to do
from dayto day it's that's an imperfect
Association and beyond that there are a
whole uh Suite of cognitive functions or
things that we do with our brain that
you can't really measure with those
tests so part of the problem is um
defining what is it that you want your
brain to do um and you almost have to
become sort of your own Baseline because
I can test your executive function and I
can test your working memory but if
you're an artist those things don't
relate to that at all um and there you
know you can do some standardized uh
tests of creativity and stuff like that
but it's just not the same so I think a
cognitive function in reality is very
personal and it depends on what you want
your brain to do and when you want your
brain to do it but I think that if we're
trying to Define brain health for one of
a better word it is having a brain that
does those things so some understanding
of what you want to do when you want to
do it and how can you support your brain
in doing that okay so the way that I pun
intended my brain puts this together is
I think about when I say brain health
I'm referring to do I have lesions in my
brain do I have brain damage and then
when I think of cognitive function I'm
usually thinking about perform right so
Reaction Time memory word recall
executive function is that a fair way to
characterize it or should I add a third
part there or I think about brain health
more holistically and in reality we know
that structure and function in the brain
are directly linked um the the brain has
quite a lot of redundancy so you can
lose function in an area and either
recover it or maybe you don't even
notice that that function is lost um so
so I wouldn't even necessarily separate
them out in that way I think it would
depend on what you're measuring so we
can measure brain health based on an EEG
signal like different electrical
activity and different regions of the
brain how those different networks are
connected we can also measure brain
health in terms of well how do you how
do you feel today because that's
essentially an integrated output of all
the different things that your brain is
experiencing so that's why I think about
brain health more broadly um and that
relates both to um
minute to- minute performance and
enhancing that as well as what's your
long-term trajectory of function and you
know are you then at risk of significant
detriment of function and dementia long
term right like clearly if I have some
physical structure damaged in my brain I
won't have the acute performance either
yeah right I'm going to have some
however that may manifest itself could
be any of the examples you said but does
that work backwards as well in other
words U because I'm maybe having a hard
time with some form of cognitive
function does that indicate some
likelihood of actually having some
structural damage as well or are those
is that street one
way because of the redundancy in the
structural systems you don't necessarily
um have a direct one toone connection um
and you'll probably lose or for some
people you lose some functions or the
the functions decline before you can see
say on brain Imaging oh yes here's a uh
some atrophy here's some loss of volume
or here's damage and in a certain area
so I think that may just be partly
because of the uh the resolution of the
things that we can measure so maybe we
get to a point where you have a really
really strong MRI and we can see in very
fine detail all the little blood vessels
and all the you know small parts of all
the regions of the brain and then you
could get a more direct connection so I
think they are very closely connected
and if you if you're losing a function
you there's probably going to be a
structural correlate of that but in all
likelihood because function is also
going to be driven by you know nutrient
status mitochondrial function some of
these other things you might start to
have issues with function before you see
a structural um issue on a brain scan or
something like that okay if then that is
true if I improve some sort of I'll just
keep calling these short-term acute
functionalities How likely is that then
to carry over into long-term brain
health
the the way that I think about the brain
is uh because I'm I'm a bit of a
meathead as you know I I enjoy lifting
weights and the more time I spent
studying the brain uh the more the
brain could uh be be thought to respond
similar to say skeletal muscle in
response to exercise so all the things
that you've spent decades researching
these processes are very similar in the
brain and what that really means is that
function is driven by stimulus just like
if you're trying to get uh strong and
jacked you need to apply uh mechanical
tension to the skeletal muscle right
regardless of everything else that you
do and you can improve you can improve
that response with sleep and nutrition
and things like that but no stimulus no
response and the brain is essentially
the same and what you see is that when
you stimulate certain networks or areas
of the brain with certain activities in
response you then see an improvement in
structure because structure comes from
that stimulus and then the way that the
brain responds to it and the brain is
capable of that pretty much throughout
the entire lifespan that's really
interesting because almost always when
we hear this stuff talked about we hear
it in the sense of neuroplasticity right
so you have a capacity issue some
neurological adaptation which you know
it is structural but for the most time
we don't think about that as a
structural change we just think it as a
functional yeah right so you have a new
capacity your action time is faster your
word Rec whatever right but what you're
actually saying is there's also a as
noticeable physical change akin to
muscle right so when I get my when I
train my muscle I have neurological
adaptations that make me stronger I also
have larger biceps I'm not assuming I
don't have a larger brain right well you
obviously the the space within the skull
is limited but to some extent you do
have a larger brain and we know that
with um Aging in particular and as you
follow trajectory say into dementia
your brain gets smaller right you get
atrophy of the brain you can then see
increases in the volume of the brain in
response to certain stimuli so you can
get particularly once the the volume of
the brain has started to decline as you
get older you can see then a response in
terms of volume with certain stimuli
so that's not just neuronal connections
um but it part of it is so you have uh
your density of connections right that's
the neuroplasticity you know new neurons
talking to each other early on in the
the loss of volume of the brain um
people think about neurons dying but
actually that happens quite late what's
happening is those neurons themselves
are just shrinking up so they're still
there they still have the capacity for
function buty before Aptos yeah and if
you're not using them right they will
then follow that trajectory but they
that can be recovered Plus neurons make
up less than 50% of the cells in the
brain you have multiple other cell types
you have a huge vascular Network in the
brain and so when you're improving
volume you're also improving other cell
types you know the extracellular Matrix
is really important in terms of all the
proteins that that sort of regulate how
the cells interact so yes you can
improve volume it's not just neurons
though and I think often we focus on
neurons but really there's so much else
going on at the same time man I'm
totally guilty of that like I just I
know certain aspects of the Brain Change
physically in a good or bad way in
response to you know perturbations but I
just always give it the the neural
plasticity twist so I'd love to come
back to that um I want to know more
about it but I got to ask since we're
right here I don't think there's any
more debate at least in my understanding
of the literature anymore about whether
or not exercise and things like that are
good for long-term brain health yeah
what there is considerable debate on
though is can you actually improve
cognitive function right now you said
this earlier if you want to do an IQ
test and then I coach you on that IQ
test you will improve yeah um you could
probably pick about every metric in the
brain possible but that doesn't
necessarily mean you're getting better
cognitive function it just means the
brain is is neuroplastic and achieves an
adaptation response to stimuli so I'm
more interested in in where you stand on
that
Global argument um first of all is there
even argument is it pretty well
scientifically established where's that
field lie and then you know overall tell
me can we actually improve cognitive
function and then for sure if we can I
want to know how so again it really
depends who you ask and how you're
measuring asking yeah you're asking me
but if you were to if you were to sample
a large number of cognitive
neuroscientists um and even some of the
people that I work with some will say
yes you can improve cognitive function
and some will say no you can't um and
this is partly driven by how we're
testing it right which we which we' kind
of covered and yes we know that um
people who spend longer in education
they have uh improved cognitive function
but part of it is just because they get
better at taking tests yeah right and
when any study does longitudinal testing
of cognitive function everybody gets
better even the control group because
they get just get better at taking the
test so then when you're thinking about
when you're thinking longterm which
we'll come back to uh I think there is a
good amount of evidence that we can
improve cognitive function when when
it's when you're in a period of decline
but then if you're thinking right now
how can I improve my cognitive function
I think the way that I think about it is
again related to skill development and
what it is that we actually want our our
brains to do and the human brain um more
so than any other species is evolved to
adapt to the environment so that it can
optimally perform within that
environment that means that whatever you
want your brain to do and if you train
it in the right way you will improve
function any skill learning language
Sports um and then beyond then when
you've done that you have improved
cognitive function right you're using
your brain to perform some skill you
have improved at that over time and your
cognitive function has therefore
improved we also know that there then
carry over from specific skill learning
to more broader cognitive function
particularly uh longer term but if you
define it that way I think that we know
that the process of skill development is
the process of enhancing cognitive
function and then it's just a case of
how do I maximize that adaptation and
how do I maximize the expression of that
skill once I've attained it today's
episode is sponsored by ag1 ag1 is a
vitamin mineral drink with probiotics
prebiotics and adaptive
initially I was extremely skeptical of
ag1 as I am with all supplement
companies but after months of
discussions with their lead nutrition
scientists and the general team at ag1
I've been impressed by a1's commitment
to sourcing the highest quality
ingredients and constantly updating
their formulas to have the right
ingredients in the optimal amounts ag1
also rigorously tests their products to
ensure that every single batch is free
of ban substances allergens heavy metals
microbes pesticides herbicides residual
solvents and microtox
it's even earned the prestigious NSF
certified for sport thirdparty testing
approval stamp now most people in the
performance space talk a lot about
macronutrients like protein
carbohydrates and fats and these are
obviously critically important but so
are the micronutrients like vitamins and
minerals and even if you're eating a
healthy diet it's often hard to get
enough of these vitamins and minerals
along with their probiotics prebiotics
and adaptogens to keep your body
performing at its best it's for these
reasons and many others that I
personally take ag1 almost every day now
it's of course not a replacement for
eating whole healthy foods but it is a
great way to make sure that you're
plugging in any gaps in your nutrition
to improve your energy bolster your
immune system and just generally help
promote a healthy gut microbiome and
more if you'd like to try ag1 you can go
to drink a1.com perform to receive five
free travel packs plus a year supply of
vitamin D3 plus K2 again that's drink
a1.com perform to receive five free
travel packs plus a year supply of
vitamin D3 plus K2 if I want to improve
creativity just do more creative tasks
yes if I want to improve memory practice
memory yes and this probably expands to
any way we would Define cognitive
function for a normal young healthy
person right so actionable step number
one would be simply that right if you
want to get better at writing WR I I
that was one of my favorite I had a a
friend several friends who are writer
and it's stunning how low energy last
minute that they can pull up smash out
3,000 words and you're like that would
have taken me months months to write
right this is what they do naturally
that makes a ton of sense where is the
broader applicability are there any
maybe specific domains of cognitive
function that have better
transferability to others uh are there
any particular types whether this is
maybe exercise or nutrition or brain
training devices or tactics that have a
a more wide ranging again broader
applicability or is it all pretty much
they're going to be good on their
individual one and then have very little
transfer so this is the principle of
near transfer versus far transfer so
near transfer means that you learn to
get good at the thing that you want to
get good at and then it doesn't really
translate elsewhere it's it's been the
problem with um brain training uh as has
typically been done for the past few
decades and that's one of the reasons
why people think you can't enhance
cognitive function is because when you
do brain training what you get better at
is just some version of the test that
doesn't then make you a better
functioning person out in the real
world but if your NE transfer is
relevant to you say it's writing or some
other kind of specific Skiller language
right then near transfer can be enough
but we also know that if you're trying
to think about uh so far transfer so
improving some cognitive function that
then translates to other cognitive
functions then activities that um train
certain aspects of decision- making in
the prefrontal in the prefrontal cortex
they seem to be associated with some uh
some Far transfer just you get you get
better at regulating your own internal
thought and decision- making processes
and that relates to a wide variety of of
scenarios then um some of the other
things that you mentioned like exercise
is one that supports and it's it's
exercise specific so resistance training
and aerobic training have effects on
different areas of the brain and both
good but different yeah both good but
different um but then that applies to to
functions more broadly right you're
going for a run and that you know
aerobic exercise is particularly good at
um improving certain aspects of memory
and so it doesn't matter what you're
memorizing right memory is is is broadly
uh enhanced so some of the the lifestyle
factors that we know are are critical
for for brainal and cognitive function
they broadly support cognitive function
as well as um skill learning in the
first place um but then some specific
skills may be you know just just related
to to to that skill as as you use it
okay I'm going to give you a couple of
avatars here and uh I'm asking this
personally imagine uh because you've
worked with athletes across I mean gez
every sport imaginable you've worked
with uh industry folks you've worked
with non-athletes uh you've done
concussion stuff you've done aging stuff
so you're you're all over the map in
terms of your skill set M so with this
uh somebody comes to you and says hey
look my brain's healthy um I'm 40 years
old I'm not super worried about
Dimension Alzheimer's things like that
I'm I'm My Lifestyle factors are
exercise I do all you know I sleep well
I don't drink I don't smoke so on and so
forth I don't have a thing I'm looking
for I don't know what I'm looking for I
maybe run a company I have kids
something like
that what should I do to enhance my
brain function right now and I can't
Define that I don't know if that means I
need to be creative I don't know if that
means I need to have more you know
reaction time
what like where would you start with
that individual in terms
of what you said at the beginning I you
should make your own Baseline test like
what should I be thinking about and are
there some tactics where you say okay I
need all the information I would really
need all but maybe two or three things
here that start off that generally work
pretty well so generally I'd think
about when somebody like that comes to
me and they say I'm healthy my brain
works great um I'd like to improve it as
much as I can or maintain it for as long
as possible the first thing is just to
make sure if that first statement is
true and the easiest way to do that is
with some simple blood tests you know
determine some like nutritional status
becomes really critical for the brain we
can um we can deal with poor nutritional
status the brain works just fine early
in life but if you're trying to you know
maximize everything we know uh vitamin D
iron status magnesium uh B vitamins
Omega-3s some of these and glucose
glucose regulation or at least just
making sure you don't have pre-diabetes
you know some of the basics I would just
make sure that all of that is sort of
buttoned up and that's and that's easy
to address would you mainly say those
are energy metabolism markers as long as
your energy metabolisms fine you're
probably okay there's an interesting
thing uh about energy metabolism in the
brain and as it relates to brain
structure as well which is that it kind
of follows a U-shaped curve so at low
levels of energy availability we start
to lose brain structure and brain
function just because we don't have the
energy to support it and then we see a
very clear energy toxicity effect as
well so if we have you know pre-diabetes
diabetes um lipid disregulation you all
the markers of energy toxicity which are
very very common right 2third if not
more adults in the US have some version
of that then you start to see a decline
in cognitive function and brain volume
as well so yes energy regulation is
really important but some of those
nutrients have their own um effects in
terms of brain structure as well so if
you think about the relationship between
B vitamins and Omega-3s this has been
shown again and again and again that
they interact so if you have good status
of one but not the other you see no
effect and vice versa and this is where
we've had trials that say we give
Omega-3s but they don't work or we give
B vitamins but they don't work but they
haven't taken the the other into account
and it makes perfect sense because if
you want DHA the longchain omega-3 fatty
acid to sit in the sinapse where you
want it you know to help communication
between two neurons it needs to first
get into the brain and that requires
usually healthy uh instant sensitivity
and energy regulation and then it needs
to go down the path of being attached to
some kind of phospholipid right so
choline or serine or ethanolamine
uh so you need that to be available and
then you need methylation to work so
these things get attached together
that's where the B Vis become important
so some of these things are directly
structural uh as well as being you know
functional thinking about energy and M
and mitochondria I don't want to lose
the plot I'll come back to our Avatar
here in a second I have many follow-ups
to that I'll I'll ask just one though I
don't think people would have assumed
you can get a reasonable assessment of
short-term immediate acute cognitive
function from blood H so uh right now
you probably can't um you and I are in
the process of uh uh developing what
should be a fairly simple uh blood test
that relates directly to cognitive
function dementia risk or morality risk
but like I said critically cognitive
function right now it's not going to be
perfect but it does relate generally to
nutritional status and energy status
which which makes perfect sense so on
top of that I think you could um you
know really button up the details with
making sure that all you have all your
nutrient ducts uh in a row but in
reality if you're going to try at the
population level at least try and
predict some of these cognitive function
you could see or if they have
pre-diabetes or any kind of um nutrient
deficiency they're going to have low
cognitive function and there's there's
you know dozens hundreds of studies that
show that do they need to necessarily be
at a technical deficiency there or or if
they're you know say bottom 10th
percentile they should pay attention do
we have any insights and where those cut
offs start to lie for these metrics yeah
it it
probably you you're right that in
general what we consider to be a a
deficiency nowadays is usually you're
below the normal range right you're in
the bottom 2.5% of some nutrient marker
and right you like you're going to have
some your day-to-day cognitive function
is not your ma your main issue right
there's going to be even bigger problems
than that but there are some cut offs
for for all of these things uh well in
in general say blood sugar regulation
you want to make sure that normal
fasting blood sugar not pre-diabetic
beyond that there's probably not that
much benefit from from from being lower
than that but something like homocystine
is a marker of methylation status um
generally if you went to a lab the
normal range is 13 15 um five to five to
like bottom end five high end 13 14 15
and most people will say you sort of
like Target below 15 in terms of
cognitive function it probably needs to
be less than 11 uh some people would go
a little bit lower than that for things
like cardiovascular disease risk um but
then uh similarly for omega-3 fatty
acids if you do something like the
omega-3 index you probably want to be
like ideally over 6% maybe close to 8%
or higher um and that like I said those
those two things inter right yeah I
would say that in our
experience if you are above N9 to 10 for
home assisting we're we're looking very
seriously at other things yeah and an
Omega you'd be surprised how many are
under five yeah like very very very very
commonly this is why you see in those
folks a little bit of basic multivitamin
and omega-3 support and all of a sudden
the brain fog is gone the decline like
it's it just disappears from these
people really quickly which is is really
of no surprise so um coming back to us
then we check those blood markers uh
then what for that
so then you can make sure that the other
lifestyle factors are sort of all in a
row and when we think about long-term
cognitive function there's kind of a a
framework for thinking about
that so sleep and all these other things
stress mitigation um i' i' definitely
you know look at all these other
lifestyle factors but if you're thinking
about enhancing cognitive function like
I said earlier I think stimulus is
really the most important thing your
avatar probably has quite a cognitively
stimulating job which we know uh
increases long-term function and
decrease the risk of dementia long term
so then I would think about a lifelong
plan of ongoing broad cognitive stimuli
so if he's never played a musical
instrument he learns to play a musical
instrument if he um all his exercise is
in the gym and it's uni modal then he
picks up an open skill sport he goes to
play pickle ball or learns to skateball
God forbid no more people playing pickle
ball don't do that Tommy um if he uh has
never spoken another language then he
then he learns the language um some of
these
things it's interesting when you look
across the literature the one activity
that probably takes a lot of these boxes
and seems to really support cognitive
function as well as mental health is
dancing and because that brings in play
like it's it's an open skill there's
music it's social um so he so dance
class with his partner right would be a
great a great way to sort of integrate a
bunch of these things together
cognitive demanding what does that
actually
mean that's a that's a question that I
actually can't answer I talk about
cognitive demand a bunch but in reality
we don't know like it's a the it's a
theoretical concept because we could put
you in an MRI scanner and we could see
which areas of your brain become active
or we could do the same thing with EEG
but in reality like how do I
quantify the stimulus that's being put
on you
um compared to somebody else I mean we
can't like what's the equivalent of
volume in the brain it like compared to
say lifting weights where I can quantify
how many bicep curls did I do um what
was the weight um you you could look at
velocity and all these other things we
can't do that with the brain so yet and
so I kind of hope that one day we'll be
able to quantify that so then we could
say this is the cognitive demand that
you're getting this is the stimulus and
this is is the adaptation that we expect
to see but right now some of it is still
a bit theoretical um and when you think
about cognitive stimulus and cognitive
enhancement one of the reasons why
there's so much controversy is because
it's actually quite a young field like
we're where exercise like cognitive
enhance the cognitive enhanc field is
where exercise science was decades ago
four or five decades ago maybe so the
principles all make sense you can see it
happen in animal models you can measure
the fact that these neurons were
activated um but how you truly dig down
and quantify the networks being
activated uh and the level of that
activation or maybe what's required in
order to see u a response that's
something that still needs to be worked
on Dance makes sense to me because you
didn't say these words but sensory input
is a huge impact here right so
proception in the case of dance it is
hearing uh you're feeling you're feeling
the other person probably you're feeling
the ground you don't want to step on
toes it is rhythmic uh different these
are all different parts of the brain if
that's a fair way to say it and now you
also have memory it's this step and this
step and this step right plus improv
improvisation all the four or five
different areas immediately make sense
when you think about something like
let's just say pickle ball you said
earlier if you are a skilled pickle ball
player then the act of playing pickle
ball is not as cognitively demanding I'm
assuming as it was the the first week
you played right now there's still some
because you're reacting to the external
environment change of Direction This is
pro proception where am I at in space
what shot am I going to make what's the
score all those things right but it's
not as high as it used to be the last
time because parts of that experience
now of where to put your hands how to
swing your Technique have been now
pushed to we'll just call it
subconscious right this is learning MH
how you get better better at sports
right yeah where the cognitive demand
piece to me sets a little bit
differently again I don't know if I'm
actually thinking about this correctly
because if I think about a day-to-day
work experience for me the dance thing
makes sense because of all those
different sensory inputs when I think
cognitive demand I'm thinking some sort
of difficult mental task I'm not
thinking like a physical body movement
right so I'm thinking if I'm reading a
scientific paper that to me feels like a
high cognitive demanding task but in
reality I can do that scrolling my fall
like pretty quickly um and huous aside
here like it does not take me long to
scroll through a paper anymore and get
the gist of do I buy it do I not buy it
shoty paper where other folks I acly
know say my just S as a graduate student
like the whole day yeah reading every
word right to get the gist of it is it
just something that is a generally hard
task if I'm doing if I'm writing is that
always going to be a high cognitive
demand if I'm sending an email is that
always going to be low um I know for
example just speaking from my
relationship if my wife gives me
information about something hang with
the kids in school that's the highest
cognitive demanding effort I will have
in my whole damn like wait who what's
the kid's name again like I just have
like I'm I have to drop everything and
complete pay attention or else it goes
to zero the next day she'll remind me
and I have zero recollection she's
probably if she listens to this she's
going to die in Anger listen because
she's like yeah it's infuriating she
does the same by the way so to the point
of saying like is it the task itself is
it novelty as long as I'm doing
something different where where do we
know that something is cog where can we
get closer to
guessing
so novelty plays a big role and it's
probably because novelty drives
attention and focus and if you're
actually going to respond to a stimulus
you need to direct attentional resources
to it so then difficulty becomes
important as well so it should be
challenging and you should be giving it
your full attention and focus whatever
it is and then those are probably some
of the prerequisites in order to see
some kind of adaptation in the
brain how you subjectively feel about a
task being difficult although I'm a big
fan of the subjective for a lot of
things in this uh case it it doesn't
really work really and it's probably
because of the way that we use our
brains nowaday nowadays what you
mentioned earlier listening to to your
wife talk about something to do with the
kids and you said the only reason the
only way that you can actually
internalize it if you like if you give
her your attention so what that tells me
is what you're what you're doing is
multitasking um and you're not actually
multitasking what you're doing is Task
switching so you're trying to pay
attention to this thing in front of you
right here and then you're trying to pay
attention to her and there's a cost
every time you do that because you have
to refocus and what happens is if is
essentially you're not doing either or
you're doing both or three things very
very poorly I think I set the world
record for highest task switching cost
Ever if I have to task s like that like
it takes I have to literally sit down
I'm like shake my head I'm like okay
hold on give me a minute okay what like
it takes the the lag it's like a bad
video game it's so long on me when I
switch tasks I'm just like I like I
focus my whole day on not doing that
because it is so catastrophic for me to
have to do that yeah I I'll I can do the
task but I'll have no memory of it yeah
be gone for forever I'm actually very
similar like I am a terrible task and
like my wife always jokes I'm a terrible
multitasker
and recently you know I've leaded into
it like the human brain cannot task
switch like that efficiently people just
can't do it um you may have to be able
to navigate that for for your job but in
reality like work by Gloria Mark shows
how um constant task switching is very
stressful
um and every time you switch a task you
have that uh that cost of time as well
as the fact that if you're distracted
from a task is it maybe a long period of
time before you ever return to it and
during that whole period of time while
you're not doing the task that you
actually want to be doing right now
there's this sort of underlying
simmering stress because you know it's
there but you're not but you're not
doing it so I think a big part of this
is that multitasking as we call it or
task switching which is very common now
email to this document you're writing to
social
media it's what uh a friend of mine
James huitt calls the cognitive middle
gear and you kind of imagine it so I
I'll keep going over to to my terrible
exercise analogies but it's kind of like
spending all your time at threshold it's
incredibly like physically tiring but
the adaptation you get from it is kind
of disproportionate to how much it
drains you yeah right yeah Yep this is
the last couple of sets that you did
where you got nothing different but you
got high fatigue yes exactly and you're
doing that with your brain all day yeah
so what you really want to do is to try
and periodize that as much as you can
right so you have your periods of
intense Focus intense cognitive
performance and that's your deep work
the time when you really need to get
stuff done and then the rest of the time
you're sort of uh uh you're doing your
sort of like your your Zone to brain
work and that can be answering emails
like some of the basic stuff as soon as
you start to do you know a ton of those
things at the same time you start to to
sort of head back into middle gear but
that's you kind of have to think about
almost polarizing your your brain use
just like a lot of people might poize
their training your lab does mostly
neonatal stuff yes right so your actual
scientific time is mostly spent in young
developing brain yeah right you've
clearly done work across the entire
lifespan
does that task switching energy increase
as you get older because I feel like
when I was a kid I could task switch
immediately I don't actually have a
recollection of it being a problem as
like a grad student but now I'm like oh
my gosh just detrimental and why I'm
asking that is I'm wondering if that is
the case could that be explaining some
part of people feeling like they have
cognitive decline feeling like their
energy lower throughout the day feeling
like their brain fog is hitting now when
in reality they're just burning more gas
and they had no idea
yeah particularly early on in life I
think the brain interacts with the
environment in the way that we should be
doing as adults and we're not doing if
you watch a kid learning how to walk
that is all they focused on right um and
essentially for the first 30 years of
life the brain is continuing to adapt
and mature and it can still respond to
stimulate after that but it takes almost
half our lifetime for the brain to F to
you know finish adapting to its
environment and that adaptation is
driven by learning these skills social
interaction language motor skills but
particularly early
on that's all the brain is is focused on
doing right I'm going to spend this next
10 minutes trying to stand up and then
I'm going to take a nap and you know you
know my brain is going to start to
figure out all the inputs that it
received during that period of time had
some days like that no doubt you know
even now yeah
and so then as you get into the teenage
years I think that you're right kids
seem to be able to to jump back and
forth continuously and that that
probably is that they are better at
focusing their attention very quickly
and I think that's partly because all
the other things that we have to deal
with when we're older aren't in place so
a lot of what happens as we get older
and we think that our cognitive function
is diminishing is actually just um a
product of of the environment as well as
the fact that we're not focusing on
tasks in the way that we should in order
to to maximize the benefit from them so
when you're trying to learn a new skill
in your 40s you obviously have less time
to do it you have kids to worry about
you probably didn't sleep very well you
know you're stressed about your job and
all these other things and then you say
oh I just can't learn a language like I
could when I was a kid but when when
you're a kid you have nothing else to do
yeah right you have your French class
three times a week and all you're doing
in that class is learning French and
you're dedicating I mean whether or not
you enjoy it or you actually paid
attention at the time right but you have
these focused periods to just work on
learning the skill whereas you're
learning French as an adult it's like
well I'll do 10 minutes of du lingo
while I'm s in traffic and then you
wonder why you're not learning French as
well as you kill when you're younger
right and some of the right some of
these adaptations do slow over time but
it's not that the adult brain can't do
it it's that we're not actually applying
the principles that we did when we were
younger in order to learn these
skills today's episode is sponsored by
element element is an electrolyte drink
mix that has an ideal electrolyte ratio
of sodium potassium and magnesium but no
sugar hydration is critical to
Performance both physical and mental
performance countless Studies have shown
that even a slight degree of dehydration
even as small as 1% can lead to
decreases in physical output and mental
performance we also know that
electrolytes are critical to proper
hydration which I've been harping on for
years but you can't do that proper
hydration by only drinking water you
need to get the right amount of
electrolytes in the right ratios and
that's why I'm a huge fan of element in
fact many of you will probably remember
that I featured element in my YouTube
series on optimizing hydration nearly
five years ago I featured element in
these videos because their blend of
1,000 milligram of sodium 200 Mig
potassium and 60 Mig of magnesium really
is unique and different than any other
electrolyte on the market and it has
great scientific support I use element
constantly particularly when I'm
sweating a lot and I routinely make it a
part of my client's optimization
programs if you'd like to try element
you can go to drink LM nt.com perform to
claim a free element sample pack with
the purches of any element drink mix
again that's drink LM nt.com perform to
claim a free sample pack okay so making
sure that we are trying to focus on
singular tasks at a time and having
potentially a little bit of a buffer
when we switch from one to the next in
terms of expectations right we're not
going to be on the next one quickly so
if we go to our our 40 year
old and we're we're back on this Avatar
he's saying okay I just kind of want to
enhance my brain function there we get
we got uh I drug us off track there
pretty quick so kind of coming back to
that what would be again your your
recommendations of things to think about
stuff that he could generally try um you
mentioned learning a new language
dualingo are there any other specific uh
brain training things um do those things
work I guess we'll even start there
nutrition supplement ation neut Tropics
like what are things we can do um in
that again I'm not diseased I'm not
hurting we'll get to that later just
feeling pretty good yeah what can I do
to make my brain skains I think most
brain training as it currently exists is
probably not enough for us to see
significant far transfer and again in
that person in in that per in that
particular avar I think we're now
starting to see a revolution in VR
particularly in AR where that might
start to change and you have very
complex environments that you have to
navigate and problem solve within and
these are some of the things that the
brain thrives on and they're delivered
via the eyes which is one of the you
know the primary stimuli that that
drives you know neural
organization and then you know all the
downstream consequences of that so
you're you know compared to looking at
puzzles on a computer screen you know
having some in-depth You Know audio and
visual stimulus in a virtual reality
environment is much more similar to the
way that we nor that we normally uh
develop complex skills um and and you
know Drive brain development so I think
we're going to see more and more of that
coming
online
even in you know regular adults and
actually in kids and older adults the
current technology for say video
games when in say a 3D a complex 3D
environment it hasn't necessarily
there's been a bit in VR so far research
I think that's going to really explode
over the next few years with like all
the devices that are now available but
even like I think the the game that has
the most research is Super Mario World
3D and people who play Super Mario World
3D for a few weeks compared to something
like Tetris or solitire see greater
improvements in certain standardized
cognitive function tests so even that
kind of new complex World your um a lot
of orientation puzzle solving High
effort High Focus yeah and like you're
going to die if you're not actually
paying attention right whereas and
probably the same in Tetris but def but
not in solitire and actually with
increasing complexity you see increasing
improvements in cognitive function so
providing these complex um you know
multi-dimensional and um multi- sensory
I think we already have some evidence
that that can improve cognitive function
in healthy adults and I think we'll only
see see more of that in in the next few
years you just gave every sub
50-year-old permission to tell their
parents I told you so I told you the
video games were okay for me
uh Fair characterization or no if
cognitive function is low either maybe
young or older aging something like a
puzzle uming brain training brain HQ is
probably the Yeah the more um most
studied one many randomized control
trials potentially could help however if
you are kind of normal to above going
past that that's just not cognitively
demanding yeah most likely not right so
now you have to get into situations
where again you care more or there's a
heart rate elevation there's some
other functional physiological demand
that provides enough of a stimuli to
cause adaptation so video games of that
ill come I'm sure there are plenty of
other ones but you get the concept right
it has to be all those things you laid
out um this is where something like a
dance would also then fit in right
learning a new skill presumably rock
climbing or surfing where your
environmental exposures and temperature
changes are great activities um Combat
Sports are of course are like fantastic
for this just don't get punched in the
head too much too much yeah um what
about from a nutrition side
supplementation side is there anything
you can do or on the ver that is there
anything that you just have to avoid are
there are there particular nutrients or
styles of eating that are really bad for
the the normal non diseased person or or
what do we know about that side outside
of energy toxicity which you talked
about longterm was a problem yeah
so in reality the answer is no there's
nothing that anybody has to avoid
there's some reasonable obser
observational epidem epidemiological
evidence to say you know highly refined
you know diets high in Ultra processed
foods which that classification is
problematic because it includes protein
powder which I would you know happily
recommend to people but also Twinkies
right I don't think look we can be
pedantic about this but a diet highend
you fill in the blank here probably not
good yeah ex I don't know if we have the
direct mechanistic research on that for
this question but we don't have to
stretch our imaginations far to say
there's so many other reasons why you
should avoid that yeah like just okay so
outside of that yeah and then that's a
lot of the downstream effects of that
are driven either by nutrient
deficiencies or energy toxicity right so
things that we've things that we've
already covered in terms of
supplementation it then probably becomes
a case of what is it that you're trying
to achieve and when you're trying to
achieve it so I think in you know
healthy individuals in athletes we see
some interesting improvements in Co in
Broad cognitive function with say
creatine supplementation M particularly
in in aspects of memory um so that's
that's something that's always high on
the list um everything else that I think
would would go on the definitely take
could also be related to the Nutritional
piece so magnesium status vitamin D all
those other kinds of
things when you're then thinking about
um say supplements or neut Tropics often
what you see is that there's a trade-off
that you enhance one function at the the
price of another and that's fine but
that has to be a choice you can't just
take these things and think I'm going to
be better at everything because the the
brain doesn't work like that well
nothing in physiology works like that
generally no free passes no free passes
no biological free lunch so then
um it's just going to depend on on what
you're trying to achieve so if you've um
you know had issues with sleep or stress
um long term then there are interesting
things like theanine ashanda ksm66 they
seem to you know improve um stress and
also cognitive function in those
settings um if you're thinking about
trying to perform in the moment in a
given sport uh so I can I can use
Formula One as an example we've worked
with multiple drivers
who because of their engineers and the
teammate they're competing against one
of one of the metrics that you can
easily see they show it on the on on the
TV right at the beginning of the races
reaction time so how quickly did this
driver get off the
line
when you try and increase that or try
and decrease or improve reaction speed
decrease reaction time then there are
some you know the the the supplement
that would first come to mind is
caffeine y right no doubt and it works
right we know that caffeine improves
psychos vigilance and it improves
reaction time however we also know that
at higher doses caffeine decreases
uh complex complex skillability right
and decreases certain aspects of EX
could imagine any scenario in which you
you would want to be driving 200 miles
an hour on a th000 milligrams of
caffeine yeah absolutely not and so this
and but it's it's been done or it's been
tried and you'll see a great reaction
time off the line and then you're trying
to navigate the first corner at 200 mil
hour 150 mph with 19 other cars around
you and you plow into the first corner
so this then comes in into the idea of
getting into the right window of arousal
for some given cognitive task and we can
use supplements to do that um but we can
also use um breathing techniques
exercise to kind of modulate some of
that so there are some supplements and
you know depending on the task maybe
caffeine is the the right one for most
people who who are habitual caffeine
users you're generally just reversing
the deficit caused by a caffeine
deficiency at the moment rather than
enhancing function which is fine
you just had coffees before we came in
here right um but then beyond that it's
going to really depend on on the task
and that's largely going to be related
to arousal what level of arousal is
going to be ideal for the task that
you're trying to perform and each task
is probably going to have a different uh
ideal level of arousal it's really
interesting you say that because with
all the athletes we work with there is a
spectrum of caffeine use uhuh not only
within the person to person that happens
but I mean as it categorically between
sports if you take
for example our NFL players they
generally on a pretty high dose of
caffeine it's a cognitive sport but our
golfers absolutely not oh yeah like you
know maybe a cup in the morning or
something like that and that that's it
maybe 50 migs or something like that
like some little little top off but they
don't want to have they can't have that
kind of neural control on very much
caffeine yeah at all many of them are
just no caffeine period right um some of
our fighting Sports they can be a little
bit of a mix depending on what kind of a
they are but they can be on all all
kinds of different areas of this I know
personally I'm kind of on likee the golf
world I generally like like one shot of
espresso yeah like that that is like
good for the day just like kind of
moldering around a little bit if I have
afternoon I want like decaf or quarter
calf then I'm like that's like perfect
for me um I have other friends who are
like the opposite right it's just like
you know six 8 10 servings a day and
they're going if I use almost any form
of neut Tropic and I've probably tried a
dozen outside of caffeine and
nicotine I can't get a word out yeah my
cognitive function goes to zero like if
if I do like a tenth of a serving like I
just I just can't use it at all but I'd
say 90% of the people we've coached with
Alpha GPC or things like that have a
positive experience so Dr Wood
why why can I not think straight I mean
I I have to think about every word that
comes out of my mouth if I do the
smallest half dose of alpha
GPC that's a really great question and
the answer is I don't know what
the the a lot of people I know really
like I've been wanting to know this for
like a decade by the way the the reason
why I can't answer that question is
because there isn't that much re like
high quality research on Alpha GPC
there's quite a lot on CDP Coline or
city so another form of Coline which um
you know people say that Alpha GPC is
more likely to get into the brain more
likely to be turned to estaline but
there isn't that much really good
quality research so when I talk about
Coline supplementation I'll always fall
back on citicoline because that's it's
much better understood so the reason why
I can't answer your question is because
I don't think anybody's re to that I
anyone that tells me things like Alpha
GPC don't work you make you're out of
your mind you're out of your mind cuz I
I I a quarter a dose I can't think yeah
straight so it absolutely works I guess
it depends on your what it means by
working how you're defining sort of work
um are there any
categorical uh pros and cons to the
things so you mentioned one earlier in
the example of caffeine you might get
enhanced reaction time but perhaps you
have a decrease in Focus or attention if
it's over stimulation are there any
other General swings like with Alpha GPC
or any other ones like we just generally
if you get more I don't know does it
even work like that if you get more
focused does that then take away
creativity or are there any other kind
of like
big switches that happen like that
there's
been as far as I know a lot less
research on those different um on those
different trade-offs there's there was a
little bit uh historically on some of
the the rasams yep um and and showed
something similar right you might have
an improvement in in some aspect of um
executive function or memory but then uh
you know verbal fluency or some other
aspect of cognitive function decreased
in response um the the stimulants
broadly have do seem to have that
trade-off that we mentioned with
caffeine so there's a recent study that
came out and compared caffeine to
methylphenidate and some of the other
stimulants that are regularly used by
students and yeah yeah you know to you
when they're studying or you know the
clinical population like ADHD who
actually you might might benefit from
them and you tend to see something tend
to see something similar so you you
might improve on one aspect cognitive
function but especially certain aspects
of executive function seem to decrease
what's interesting is that a lot of um
you see this in the uh say the
Psychedelic um micro doing literature um
you see it in the Cannabis
literature people think they're more
creative or they think they have
improved cognitive function but actually
if you measure it objectively they don't
and it it actually paralleled some of
the caffeine research where people you
just set the whole internet on fire
sorry um and so what what often happens
is people think they're functioning
better and this has happened in some
caffeine studies as well they think
they're functioning better but actually
objectively they're functioning worse so
there's this decoupling of the
subjective and the objective again um
and none of this is inherently bad it's
just knowing what it is you're trying to
achieve in the given moment what what is
that because you see the same thing in
sleep literature if you sleep deprived
people not even to extremes 6 hours a
night things like that you'll see
routinely cogn function decreases like
massively with almost not always but a
lot of times no subjective change yeah
so people think I'm totally fine I'm
totally fine I'm totally fine and then
on a standardized test they're hot
garbage like what what's actually
happening that makes you feel like here
is it just the acute self-preservation
something must be going on here that is
catastrophic or important so we're going
to maintain like total short-term focus
and just disregard like the real world
like what is happening here it's funny
because you often see the opposite in
sleep literature which is where you know
like Ellen Langer's work where they
randomized people to sleep for8 hours
but they told them they slept for 5
hours right so they slept a perfect
amount and but they thought I didn't
sleep well therefore I'm not going to
perform well and they and they don't
perform well because they because they
have this expectation so I
think for for some of it there's there
is this aspect aspect of what do you
expect to happen and thoughts Drive
physiology like we know that's the case
but and there's ton you we can do that
across blood sugar control um sleep um
even how physical activity affects
mortality we've done it with lifting
weights mhm we we actually put different
numbers on the barbell we ran a couple
of these random uh of uh deception
studies yeah with it yeah like you will
definitely PR yeah if you think the bar
is 15 pounds lighter than it is you will
absolutely PR they've done it with the
anabolic steroids right that was the one
of the most famous ones yeah that what a
one yeah so some of it is just purely
driven by expectation and I think this
translates into everything in terms of
how we think about our cognitive
function is like what are we expecting
from ourselves today and that becomes a
self-fulfilling prophecy because our
thoughts Drive our physiology and then
you get the result that you expect but
sometimes like you said you in in in the
opposite scenario where you haven't
slept well you think you're fine and you
can still measure um and you know an
objective decrease in
function there is still some like
Baseline requirement that we have these
things in place for cognitive function
so some of it's driven by expectation
but expectation isn't going to be enough
to overcome right really significant
defit yeah and we saw this a ton at
Absolute rest initially and we've seen
this in in various aspects
where set and setting and habit override
most small effect yeah in other words if
you wake up in the morning and you brew
coffee and then you walk your and you do
the whole routine and then you sit down
on your computer and then you start
writing then that is going to have a
massive neut Tropic effect not
necessarily simply because of the
caffeine in that particular case but
because your brain body knows the
pattern of when we get down here this is
when we do our deep work right so if one
day you got switched out something else
there you would not have as much of a
problem as you would maybe if the
setting is Switched right so this it's
not that the caffeine deer didn't work
it's the whole set and setting that
brings the experience from a sleep
perspec Ive if you have a certain habit
a certain behavior that then promotes
quality sleep or does the opposite
that's the pattern that you'll see right
so you can try all the sleep supplements
you want it's not going to matter if you
have this chaotic yeah like sleep
routine right so you're not saying that
those things aren't doing anything it's
just that the benefit is potentially
only going to be seen if the rest of the
situation is captured yeah and clear
because there's just too much noise in
that overall system and that makes a ton
of sense um from me um we've mentioned
this stuff a couple of times but I want
to go back just a little bit to our
Avatar let's say that person's good we
did as much as we could on him but now
let's say he or she is saying okay I'm
not normal cognitive function I don't
think I have brain disease it's brain
fog right I'm just and it's not
perceptive it is noticeable it is real
there's this big decline um you hear a
lot of these certainly the last couple
years about potentially long Co I
happened when I after I got Co or didn't
or got a whatever just for whatever
reason we're down
there how does somebody know what that
actually is uh how are there tests that
you can take are there online surveys or
things that the average person could try
and then secondly you know get what do I
do to improve
that this is another controversial area
the idea of brain fog which
I kind of use interchangeably with the
more formal definition which is
subjective cognitive decline that's
brain fogs way nicer sound so when when
you look at the um the sort of the
stages of dementia now they they include
some of these some of these periods so
first you know everything's good no
subjective or objective change and then
next there's probably a subjective
decline before you see an objective
change in function right or at least
that's assuming that you don't have
years of longitudinal cognitive function
test in this person which nobody has so
if you you feel like I have this brain
fog I feel like something's not quite
right but if I gave you a bunch of
standardized cognitive function tests
you'd be within the normal range and I'd
say there's nothing wrong with you right
but there's quite a lot of research now
suggesting that that subjective decline
which you know has a lot of overlap with
the idea of brain fog then is a
associated with improve improve or
increased risk of first M cognitive
impairment which is like the next step
of cognitive decline and then dementia
obviously not everybody who gets brain
fog is going to get dementia right I
don't want to say that right now you
just terrified the internet you set them
on fire earlier now they're all
terrified that and and that so that is
definitely not true it's but I think the
fact that they are linked at least at
the population level statistically
suggests that that could be a signal of
some kind of impending issue or the
beginnings of initial of of an initial
issue now most of that in that in that
stage is thought to be reversible even
if you ask you know Dusty old
neurologists who think about who thought
about this they would tell you and that
if you look at the this the sort of the
spectrum that's in published papers
they'll say that at this stage it's
reversible so then you have to think
about well what are the potential
contributors to this
and there are just the same old Basics
that are going to come up again and
again and again and so we we already
covered the nutrition stuff that is that
like you said you've even seen that um
in your own clients right you address
some basic nutritional things and a lot
of this stuff lifts immediately I'd
probably say 60% of our
clients have a subjective score of of
cognitive function of five or less out
of 10 yeah right so whether they
actually have brain for don't like over
half of our people think that their
brain is functioning poorly yeah and I
would say our success rate is over 90%
with all that yeah we've done lot
sometimes it is more complicated but a
lot of the times if you cover all the
bases we have stunningly High results
and that makes perfect sense if you
think about or if you think about the
the framework of how I think about
cognitive function and so maybe that's
this is the time to kind of bring that
um and because it then relates to
long-term cognitive decline as well
so to kind of fit all these different
pieces together we've we've touched on a
lot of them I have what I call now the
3s model which is stimulus Supply and
support and these are the three broad
categories of the things that are
required to maintain and sustain
cognitive
function
and some inputs will cover many of those
at the same time right so they like
sometimes i' I've I've put up a picture
in a lecture and said here's here's my
model and somebody's like yes but
something goes there and there I'm like
yeah I know but pict yeah it's just a
picture right just kind of simplify it
but we've talked about stimulus and I
think that's the primary driver of a lot
of cognitive function but in order to
respond to stimulus we need a few things
so in the supply bucket we have um good
cardiovascular function right um what
you see in the brain when you have an
increase in activity in some Network
associated with some function is you see
an increase in blood flow and direction
of resources to the area of the brain um
this is the process of neur vascular
coupling right so when neurons become
active blood vessels in in that area
dilate we D we direct um resources to
that
area this requires a healthy vascular
system right and so as it's almost
exactly the same process of as what
happens in the coronary arteries in the
heart as we get into the process of
heart disease and therefore there's a
lot of overlap in risk factors for heart
disease and risk factors for dementia
and cognitive decline probably because
of that vascular component so everything
that would improve cardiovascular heal
Health then helps to support this
exercise being one but obviously other
aspects of maintain you know making sure
you have low cardiovascular risk blood
pressure you know lipids if necessary
all those kinds of
things then you need some kind of energy
source right for most parts of the brain
most of the time it's going to be
glucose uh but it certainly could be
lactate it could be ketones right so and
they need to get there and they need to
be able to get to get to get across and
that that's where some of the energy
toxicity piece comes into play um and
then you need nutrients to build and
maintain the structures of the brain and
we've talked about Omega-3s and B
vitamins being critical components so
that's kind of that's the supply part
right if you want to actually create a
response to a stimulus you need all of
those things in place then you the
support side is a few things one is are
you allowing the opportunity for the
brain to respond to stimulus and again
to return to our uh gym analogy
everybody knows you don't get bigger in
the gym you get bigger when you rest
right and the brain is exactly the same
so sleep being critical to that um an
absence of chronic uncontrolled or
uncontrollable stresses is a big Point
as well and when I've like
tried we're currently writing a paper
that sort of like lays out this in a in
a more Academic Way um s like a approach
to cognitive function and when you talk
about stress in the support side even
sort of like other neuroscientists in
the field of people get a little bit um
uncertain about that because when you
look at stress and what it does to the
brain in many senses it is a cognitive
demand it creates like neuronal hyper
metabolism so you almost have to think
about it as overtraining right so it's
preventing the ability right it's it's
junk volume for your brain it's
preventing the ability to to to adapt
so that's part of it and then you also
want to avoid um any kind of uh
exposures that prevent some of these
adaptations from happening so Al you
know excessive alcohol smoking you know
air pollution is really common um and
so if you're trying to address brain
fong in an individual these are all the
areas that you have to think about right
you have to think about um energy
metabolism vascular health um sleep
stress other exposures uh we already
talked about nutrient status
and there you know some other things
that can inhibit this process include
chronic chronic inflammation so that's
where I think long covid starts to come
into play and we know that you can see
chronic inflammatory processes in the
brain you know in certain individuals
who have um ongoing symptoms after covid
you see the same thing often years or
decades after certain traumatic brain
injuries and the amount of residual
inflammation that you have in the brain
um relates to then cognitive function or
cognitive deficits in that individual
how you address that becomes tricky but
that's also not going to be necessarily
relevant to the vast majority of people
who might be experiencing these things
so that framework I think gives you then
a chance to say well where is the is the
likely deficit or where is the issue
that we're most likely to F you know
going to see benefit and why it's also
important I think to think about it in
that kind of framework is
that these risks and components aren't
linear like when we when we talk about
risk factors for cognitive decline or
cognitive issues you just get a list of
12 some people it's 50 risk factors and
they talk about it as if you have to hit
all of them perfectly in order to see
improvements in cognitive function and
that's actually not true they interact
and they synergize so we know that if
you have high blood pressure uh you
offset some of that risk if you sleep
better and if but if you don't sleep
well you'll offset some of that risk if
you do exercise so you don't have to
perfectly hit everything in order to
like plug all the holes in the roof
which is one of the analogies that's
kind of used for these processes
actually you can pull a few levers a
little bit and you'll you'll then almost
see or often see outsid benefits so
before we transition to this next area
if I had to summarize if I feel like my
cognitive function is fine I'm not
having any deficit right now now but I
wanted to improve it then searching for
novel tasks mhm is probably the way to
go ideally ones that have multiple
sensory inputs so smell memory different
forms of cognitive function
creativity U executive function like
different aspects now will task of there
and
avoid ex you know extended or continuous
task switching because we know that's a
significant stressor that's going to be
very relevant to the Avatar that you%
yep thank you for that
if on the opposite where I feel like I
have some sort of
cognitive dysfunction I've lost it then
we go after the 3s model and we figure
out
presumably where in the where area of
that I'm struggling the most with so is
it the the supply area is it
um the other ones so yes so Supply and
support or it could still be stimulus
right or stimulus right so maybe I'm not
doing enough different things maybe
there's some hole somewhere so more than
likely you've got a hole in your game
somewhere yeah that's either then
causing excessive energy you feel like
your energy is low but what's actually
happening is you're burning a lot of
energy you don't really realize it
because your stress load is high yeah
and that's actually literally burning
fuel in your brain right to keep that
managed um I would say of the people I'm
talking about that we coach at r that
has that 90% um I don't think we've seen
anybody that has a problem outside of
that yeah oftentimes they think that
they are for sure convinced that there's
something off the- wall going on and
that has occasionally happen but most of
the time I'm I'm not simply saying the
basics most of the time if we do a full
true analysis of sleep Stress Management
movement daily uh format so how your
actual life is structured hydration and
um Mental Health on top of nutrition
blood work things like that something is
generally very very bad yeah and they
may not see that perceive that
but once we get that cleaned up
sometimes it's been as simple honestly
as hydration yeah that's that um I
didn't mention that but would you know
fits right into that supply side right
stunning a CR a critical component
sometimes it's low sometimes it's high
I've talked about this so many times now
but particularly females they just
stress drink water they just chug it and
we're like you can't drink two gallons
of water a day I'm being a little bit
hyperbolic but not much there and you
lower that back to normal and like
headaches go away function comes comes
back and you're like oh I feel smart
again so th those are I think really
insightful things that we can do
mhm today's episode is sponsored by
Renaissance periodization if you want to
put on muscle through science-backed
training programs look no further than
renaissance periodization renaissance
periodization guides users through
effective and easy to follow strength
training programs all through their
hypertrophy app these programs are
designed by the absolute best in the
industry including one of my favorite
sport scientists and professional
bodybuilders Dr Mike Israel you may
recognize that name because I referen
him and his work countless times over
the years whether you're looking to put
on muscle gain strength or both these
programs will help you achieve your
goals and have produced results in
thousands of men and women Renaissance
periodization also has a diet app that
is backed by the latest science and
innovation in the field of nutrition and
takes a complexity out of dieting
helping you achieve your ideal body
composition if you'd like to try
Renaissance periodization go to rpst
strength.com
perform to save up to $50 off your
subscription again that's rpst
strength.com perform to save up to $50
off of your
subscription last little thing I want I
want to ask about before we move forward
to something you've kind of been
alluding to but that is Vision
training you mentioned reaction time and
I'm bringing this up because we see this
actually a lot with our athletes and
people tend to not realize it the first
time I caught wi to this was actually a
number of years ago working with high
level major league baseball players
there's some actually some cool work out
of Japan it found that the variance in
major league baseball players the
batting success so batting average it
was something absurd like 70% of varians
was all in visual like auar metrics
explained almost everything and that's
when I was like whoa if we really think
we're going to service our baseball
players better if we're not touching and
testing and monitoring and improving
Vision like we're spit we're going after
pennies yeah on the dollar here so what
do we know about testing Vision outside
of of course you need glasses like
things like that and then like can I get
that tested how do I get that tested and
then what do I do to improve it if I
can't test and just again are there
exercise are there breath work are there
nutrition how do we improve Vision
supplements whatever the case may be
recently we've done some work um also in
Formula 1 drivers with vision because
this is a big part of their um a part of
their job and it's essential they'll
probably you start to lose some visual
accurity before you're going to lose a
lot of other functions the eyes are an
extension of the brain essentially so a
lot of the stuff that we just talked
about actually applies here as well um
really so that basic stuff should
improve Vision as well yeah and I did
some analyses with some large population
data sets um in order to try and answer
some of this question of course it's in
a general population but if you're
looking at different aspects of visual
Acuity even just measured with like a a
standard test you'll see that blood
sugar control nutrient status all of
these things also you know smoking and
all that kind of stuff all those same
risk factors that we know are important
for cognitive function they then relate
to to visual Acuity as well so those
same principles come into play and all
those same nutrients are going to be
important as well because you you're
essentially firing neurons from the eye
into the brain right it's it's it's the
same process when you then think about
uh visual
assessment um there are a whole bunch of
different platforms that you can do do
this with depending on you know how much
money you have and what you have access
to but like right ey is is one that's
you know fairly good certainly looks at
different aspects of eye tracking which
is important um for athletes but also
after concussions and things like that
you can also do much more complex um eye
Imaging like Optimal tomography they can
give you a much better idea of the the
the structure of the eye itself and if
there's any potential issues
there when you then think about visual
training a lot of it comes down to
similar principles and actually there's
a big overlap between um your visual
training and both physical and cognitive
training because part of it is
neurological and part of it is physical
right you are training muscles in the
eye so when we start to lose visual
Acuity you can in reverse that with
essentially Progressive overload of um
the ocular muscles by just trying to
focus on something that's just beyond
the the reach of your of your current
visual
Acuity similarly if say it's like dark
light contrast is the same we spend a
lot of time exposed to the same
um intensity of light indoors um and so
then we that may be part of the reason
why we lose some um dark light contrast
as we get older there's a nutritional
piece as well but like how often do we
see and try and see in true dark and how
often do we see in bright light and it's
not that often because we're not
exposing us ourselves to those
differences um in in light levels so you
can then do um training with like visual
tracking so when I was trying to put
together a program uh to for for say a
Formula One driver that that that want
to try and maintain visual tracking
there are some off the-shelf things that
you can use there's some nice evidence
for something like neurot tracker um
where you do multiple object tracking um
that's probably not nearly as complex as
you would need to do when driving a
Formula 1 car but for somebody who's
done no visual training there's some
reasonable evidence to say that multiple
object tracking just on your computer
can improve some aspects of of vision
and then beyond that it's just thinking
how do you create more and more complex
situations where you you then train
these muscles so um I spoke to a friend
of mine who's uh a former Special Forces
and does a lot of this kind of training
with individuals and so one of his
favorite uh tasks is to use a baseball
that you hang on some kind of string and
then you have um either letters or some
kind of symbols on it so then you can
first start with uh the ball just
hanging still and vertical and then you
can practice say focusing on the far
distance focusing on uh a symbol on the
ball then focusing even closer right so
you can practice uh quickly switching
visual depth but then you can also do
things like make the pendulum swing and
then you have to track you know a
certain symbol as the ball rotates and
then also do that by Chang by quickly
changing visual fields and so then
you're essentially TR um training all
these different parameters of vision
both visual field as well as um you know
looking all the different directions
that you might choose to look so the
extremes of peripheral vision and as
well as up upgaze and DOW gaze and it
seems that right you probably can't
overcome a huge visual deficit right but
a lot of these different uh features of
vision do seem to be
trainable there's a old thing we used to
do in baseball where you have a bucket
of balls and you throw balls to a hitter
and the hitter has to identify ify
different numbers and letters right so
you're going imagine you got a bucket of
balls there and you got a one on one of
the balls the next ball has a B on it
and so like that and you throw it in the
batter and only has to hit the ball but
then say that was four that was F things
like that yeah are you telling me that
that might plausibly actually work
yes you Vindicated every 1980s basball
hitting coach normal normally it's like
some of these uh old school training
methods just seem like hazing and uh
they kind of these attritional processes
but some of it might actually work okay
so could do things like that we see this
a lot of the times in Combat Sports and
stuff as well we throw different numbers
out there I think what you said at the
beginning then makes a ton of sense this
is it's the same exact principles of
training your muscle which were the same
as training your physical brain yeah and
now you're eye right it is Progressive
overload it is stimuli it is changing
things is a variety and then it is
intention and focus so you couple those
things together you could probably come
up with just about any drill yeah you
really wanted it like doesn't matter a
whole heck of a lot um vitamin A keratin
like what what about things like this it
makes sense if you Wikipedia really
quickly what those things are um for
clearly there's evidence if you've got
certain physical cognitive or physical
issues in your eye especially from like
a vitamin A deficiency yeah then of
course it's going to work but for the
normal person and the reason I'm asking
this is I know of multiple companies now
that sell very specific very expensive
supplements for vision yeah for normal
vision to enhanced vision for Special
Forces for certain sporting populations
I know you don't know the data on all
these I don't even know them but in
general is it plausible that they work
is it completely implausible or do we
not know so a lot of supplements that we
use to boost any function or are used to
boost any function like testosterone
boosters or these kind of visual
boosters they there's probably going to
be a benefit in the setting of an
insufficiency or deficiency but then
increasing above that you're not you
you're not going to see um any benefit
for some people um right retinol is
important we know retinol is important
in the eye some people du to genetic
polymorphism aren't as good at
converting be kosene into retinol right
so maybe there's some indiv inter
individual variability there but no like
more isn't isn't going to be better um
certainly other things do seem to
suggest some benefit and it's kind of
like squint a bit and and it might help
but some of the antioxidants you know
lutein asanin zanthin they seem to be
associated with improvements in
cognitive function and sometimes a
supplement there were trials that show
some of those supplements can improve V
visual Accu and some other aspects of
vision yeah actually that's like
reasonably well demonstrated at this
point my ass my question with those
trials are
always are you simply seeing a metric of
somebody who had suboptimal physiology
oh I'm sure yeah probably in most
scenarios because we know that most
people have some nutritional requirement
or you know metabolic health issue or
something like that so then if you're
you have a bunch of oxitive stress in
your eye because you're pre-diabetic
then you know uh uh an antioxidant then
can that can get into that system is
likely to show benefit yeah right um
which is not to say you shouldn't use it
yeah right if this is your first entry
into enhancement for that individual as
a coaching tool that that happens right
sometimes you struggle with people and
you're like you know what I'm just going
to give them an easy win because we've
been trying the nutrition we've been
trying to not get get to stop drinking
as much as they won't but then they see
benefit there so I actually don't want
to dismay that too much um we take a
different approach of course
generally and so we haven't really seen
much benefit yeah in those folks but I'm
not I'm not surprised by that so you've
mentioned this multiple times now
whether it be from the energy toxicity
or your
uh metabolic and energy sustained
principles with cognitive function but
I'm wondering like how
specifically things like PR actually
enhance brain function we you can take
this actually from both angles this is
like actual cognitive function first of
all does it like if I take right
now am I going to have a Improvement in
cognitive function and then what about
long-term brain as well so kind of
two-part question there about creatine
specific I guess we'll just start there
yeah and then how actually it's it's
doing those if it is at all so whether
you would see a significant benefit from
creatine right now probably depends a
littleit you take your dose of 10 G RS
and like what are you going to see uh it
probably depends a little bit on your
context
but you you probably saw the recent
paper that showed that after one night
of sleep deprivation you know creatine
can overcome some of those deficits
cognitively cognitively yeah and that's
like that was actually shown um a few
years ago uh with skill rugby skills in
rugby players you may have seen that
paper as well where they had players
after a period of sleep deprivation they
gave them either creatine or caffeine
and saw similar improvements in uh like
rugby specific skills compared to a
placebo yeah with a very different
mechanism here right you're talking
about a stimulant and versus a fuel
right totally opposite yeah so uh
however you could probably relate both
of those to energetics in some way
because caffeine is overcoming or it's
inhibiting the metabolic downregulation
caused by adenosine um which is part of
what drives you know sleep pressure in
the need for sleep as you accumulate
metabolites like adenosine they then um
sort of suppress metabolic activity in
the brain um which then is associated
with reduced function and something like
caffeine overcomes that whereas creatine
can acutely uh provide a buffer uh an
energetic buffer that allows you to
maintain function in the face of um sort
of increasing metabolic pressure to to
sleep so even though different
mechanisms they kind of maybe converge
on on something
similar I know a lot of people who you
know every time they take creatin they
notice like an immediate sort of boost
of some kind cognitive function yeah um
and there's there's been a lot of
discussion over the years about whether
creatine negatively impacts sleep um for
that reason it's sort of it's slightly
stimulating for some people um I've
certainly found that in myself like if I
take c i I work out in the afternoon if
I take creatine after my workouts I
don't sleep as well but if I take it
first thing in the morning it's fine
because I've kind of separated it away
and not everybody's like that and
certainly we know that uh responses to
creatine are very hetrogeneous right
some people see totally big uh big
responses some people see see smaller
responses and some of it may be related
to methylation status because creatine
uh when we make our own which we make a
lot of is the most methylation intensive
process in the body you spend Mo like
more of your methal groups producing
creatine than anything else um and so it
could be related to that as well as you
know a whole host of you know how much
creatine do you normally have in your
diet and and things like that so if I've
gotten genetic testing done and I'm a no
no don't do it sh don't go
there okay
so I think based on your reaction maybe
have just give us a a little bit of an
insight into your fever favor favor
there
so um whenever whenever somebody talks
about methylation they immediately start
talking about genetic testing and
there's a lot of that out there right
now yes genetic polymorphisms do uh
change the functional level of enzymes
related to methylation the one that
people talk about the most is MTHFR um
different um you different polymorphisms
within uh MTHFR change the activity of
that
enzyme you know in a test tube right if
I take right in theory and then they do
in some ways relate to other markers of
methylation so um cine we mentioned
briefly earlier is is a is a is an
important marker for you know risk
factor of a wide variety of diseases
it's directly related um to your current
methylation
status
um but in most cases an elevation of
homocysteine related to those PO
polymorphisms is driven by some kind of
nutrient deficiency or insufficiency
sometimes your requirement is slightly
higher because of a polymorphism but in
general I have yet to see a study that
would change my mind when I
say I can tell everything I need to tell
from a blood test I can tell from your
phenotype and there's no additional
information that I get from your
genotype whereas the opposite is not
true if I just measure your genetics I
don't know what's going on with you and
I still need to measure your your your
your B vitamin levels and your B vitamin
status your methylation status so for
most people measuring those
polymorphisms is not helpful but what it
does is it drives a huge out of fear cuz
people are like I'm a poor methylator
like what does that even mean like
you're continuously methylating right
you if you're if you don't methylate you
die right you can't turn genes on and
off you literally can't do anything so
we create this massive nobo around uh
these different polymorphisms which I
think is is net harmful when yes
sometimes this is an issue but if you
have a significant um decrease in MTHFR
function like in air quotes um related
to an MTHFR polymorphism all you have to
do to see a significant reduction in SE
homosysteine is make sure that you're
eating the recommended daily allowance
of
riboflavin like it's it's it's not hard
it's it's literally nothing and that's
because the polymorphisms change how
MTHFR bind to fad which is the the
proton carrier that that enzyme uses so
all you need to do is slightly increase
availability of riboflavin to be
converted into fad and that's it and it
doesn't require super dooses just
literally just 2 milligrams a day it's
nothing there's also a very low
relationship between those polymorphisms
and actual homoy oh yeah like very sub
1% so I've yeah and I've published a
paper on that actually for that exact
reason I I I did these uh big simulation
studies looking at the the normal
distribution of homosysteine by MTHFR
polymorphism from published data and
essentially about 1% of your
homosysteine is predicted by by your
level of activity of your MTHFR enzy
yeah so why not just measure the homo I
did a whole episode on genetic testing
in season one so please feel free to go
back and listen to that if you want um
so we we'll move on for now because we
can get aggressive there but I I think
what potentially is interesting here is
say somebody has done that testing so it
doesn't matter they've already paid the
money they're in so you know tough luck
and potentially they've had or think or
or are actually low with methylation
status would that person then
potentially be more likely to be a hyper
responder to for that exact
reason or would that's what I've
hypothesized but I and maybe this
studies if this study has been done
somebody sent it to me because I'd love
to see it but I I think that might be
the case that would make sense because
so much
um like so much of your methylation
currency is spent on creating production
if you know you have to decrease some of
that production because you know you're
quote unquote a poor methylator or you
have poor methylation status poor B
vitamin status then it would make sense
that you would sacrifice some creatine
production um and then would respond
better to creatine supplementation uh
but so in theory yes but I don't think
anybody's actually looked at that I
wonder if it works the opposite way then
as well so somebody who's had
potentially uh it will exclude Placebo
which is a large P portion of this but
uh people that have had had some sort of
genetic testing done then gone on high
doses of B vitamins and felt a massive
response I wonder if those people could
also then simply just go to
instead yeah which is I won't say safer
but a little bit less uh risky right um
not a lot of downside to not a
lot of downside to B vitamins but more
MH like you're you're going to get other
consequences that you maybe didn't
realize you're you're going after with
high doses of depending on which vitamin
vitamin B you go after um but less
potential downsides yeah I would think
you can go after what's what's
interesting is that
unfortunately these kind of questions
haven't really been addressed in the
literature right so I I can quote
studies on supplementing with B vitamins
in individuals with elevated
homosysteine and right we know we know
how that can be important and but then
we can also talk about studies where
they give doses of creatine and
particularly when you've start
particularly in older populations and
those who Maybe started to see some
element of cognitive deine you see a
greater effect size of supplementing
with creatine but I don't think
anybody's looked at like what if you
gave one or the other or is there a
trade-off um these are like super
interesting and important questions but
because of the the sort of the
reductionist evidence-based medicine
model that we currently have we just
like try one thing at a time and don't
necessarily consider the context around
it I vitamin B is I'm all four that's
great I just know that a reasonably high
percentage of people will get really
nauseous or have GI distress from them
and so for those folks potentially maybe
creatine is a little bit of an
alternative option if you think you have
a mulation or actually do either way and
B vitamins don't sit well with you yeah
especially that dosage and maybe
creatine gives you some percentage of
that benefit as well certainly we've
done um you know so you know when I was
working with a lot of individuals in you
know in a similar Arena to to what you
do now um you this is taking get you
people with their blood work and
providing individualized protocols this
is what you've done for a very very long
time yeah and when and this is sort of
like general population as well as with
athletes and if um you know B vitamin
status looked okay but maybe hyem was
still elevated or you know you we needed
other strategies to help bring down
homosysteine then creatine and choline
um or lethin which is a you know a plant
a plant derived um source of phosph
choline um they they were were good
alternative options or something you
could add on top yeah
okay why then does creatin help with
cognitive function if it does and we'll
get back to that second part of that
two-part question um is it the
methylation support that it's giving you
is there other mechanisms what exactly
is greetin doing for the brain I
think one one of the things that I found
most interesting across strategies that
seem to improve like robustly improve
cognitive function um either across the
lifespan or in multiple different groups
is that they usually do more than one
thing and anytime we've tried something
that only does one thing it doesn't work
yeah that's just like a lesson from
Neuroscience in general and also a lot
of um uh just like developing drugs in
in medicine in general yeah um and so I
think it's probably going to be a bit of
all these things so uh we know that that
home assisting is a risk factor for
congressive decline um and that's
probably because it's a marker of
methylation status right so are you able
to uh generate say membranes in in cells
in the brain like we talked about
earlier but equally uh homocystine can
directly increase the accumulation of
hyper phosphorated tow which is one of
the sort of markers of you know risk
factors of dementia it's a marker of you
know previous brain trauma and a number
of other things so it may contribute to
cognitive decline in a number of ways
and so if creatine is offsetting some of
that issue you may have some benefit
there then there's the energetic piece
right it's a it's it's going to give you
shortterm short-term energetic buffer as
phosphocreatine um in neuronal cells and
the brain is the most metabolically
expensive organ in the body on like a uh
you know calories per or watts per gram
um comparison and so you know anytime
you have either a suppression of
metabolism say uh you know adenosine or
some kind of acute injury uh and that
can either be it could be a stroke it
could be Cardiac Arrest it could be
brain trauma where you have um some kind
of deficit in energy production then
creatine also seems to potentially be
beneficial although um some of the
studies suggest you can supplement
afterwards but most of the benefit seems
to be if it's on board beforehand and of
course a lot of this evidence comes from
from animal models because you can't do
that you know easily in in humans so
some of it is an energetic buffer and
then some of it um you know one thing
that creatine seems to do is to help
stabilize and regulate calcium handling
in mitochondria um which is related to
acute injuries but also to to long-term
um mitochondrial function which then
supports long-term um cell function in
the brain really quickly I don't want to
drag this down too far but you've
mentioned it multiple times what is
methylation so why does it matter and
just real quick on this yeah so
methylation is basically the the
transfer of methal groups which is BAS a
one carbon group or a carbon with uh
three hydrogens that gets moved around
and uh this is used to uh convert
different metabolites um in in in the
body in like multiple different
stellular reactions like you you change
a a molecule from one end to another by
methylating it but it's also really
important for things like um Gene
regulation so people might have heard of
biological age
epigenetics the major um form of
epigenetics and uh Gene regulation and
you know the the sort of the more common
measures of epigenetic biological age
all are all based on methylation status
so you have uh these what called cpg
Islands on DNA which is where
essentially the cell puts on these
methylation tags which regulates whether
a gene is turned on and off and these um
these tags seem to shift over over time
that's associated with bi biological
aging so it's this really Central
process that drives you know
so many different parts of biology it's
in every cell yeah of your body it's on
DNA it's on protein it's moving a carbon
is hard yeah like chemically right so
it's got to be a major thing to get it
to move off of one which changes the
entire function yeah mole so it's I
think the way that you st it is very
nice it's it's a core biological thing
uh you don't adapt you don't grow you
don't shrink you don't go any direction
without mulation so thank you for that
now we have a little bit of
understanding of why that's
important um then regarding the
in the brain
the second part you said was fueling MH
all right walk me through how creatin
actually you mentioned it kind of
quickly uh with just a touch of jargon
there which yeah uh for the folks that
don't know what an intermediate and a
substrate are yeah how is creatine
actually providing fuel for your brain
um and then on the second part of that
is what's the normal fuel yeah for our
brain when you think
about uh different Energy Systems and I
think people could uh watch endless
lectures from you talking about
different Energy Systems in in uh in
exercise and those principles in some
ways are very similar um in the brain
although the majority of cells in the
brain are you know like like we said
earlier derived uh derive energy from
glucose goes through glycolysis then
enters the electron you know the
pyrovate and or lact Pate goes into the
electone transport chain in the
mitochondria but there's all of that is
done to generate high energy phosphates
VI usually or mainly ATP right so ATP is
your energy
currency sort of a much shorter term um
energy currency or that allows you to
recycle ATP when you've used it up is
the phosphocreatine system so um your
creatine is phosphorated with a high
energy phosphate and you use that to
regenerate ATP so for very energetically
expensive uh processes where you can't
get enough energy through that longer
process that glycolysis and aerobic
metabolism then the buffer comes from
the fossil creatine system and it seems
that even for normal cognitive function
um there is some benefit from having
more of that buffer on board um uh both
acutely and and chronically so just like
your muscles yeah or any other part of
your system they have to rely on energy
the nerves need energy to conduct right
and so people I guess sometimes don't
always grasp the fact that you're brain
when we say it's energetically demanding
it's because it's going through a ton of
metabolism we have this connotation that
muscle and Metabolism yeah kind of thing
but the brain is metabolism yeah as well
your basil metabolic rate the amount of
energy you burn throughout the day
you're fast or slow metabolism all these
things are it's in your brain yeah as
well and so it produces energy much like
anything else it can use fat as a fuel
source theoretically it can use
carbohydrates it could use ketones or
anything else and then creatine uh just
like it is in your muscle provides that
stochiometry of of one to one right so
not a lot of energy per molecule of
creatine so it gets used up and turned
and burned quickly but the upside is it
gives you that energy really fast and so
while you're maybe slow to
metabolize and you mentioned this so
I'll bring it up your brain will
actually then generate lactate yeah so
if you're thinking really hard and
thinking a long time are you like
feeling the burn in your brain is that
lactate building up is that what
happening I don't think uh lactate
doesn't accumulate it just gets
generated and and used you probably
couldn't um you you could you could
probably measure um so so this is where
I think creatin becomes important and
and you potentially if if I put micro
dialysis needles really you know
accurately in certain parts of the brain
and then you you start to upregulate the
use of that Network for a specific
function because there's going to be a
slight delay
between increased ATP production um and
the requirement right you need you you
actually need that energy before you
realize you need it right everything
that we see and do has essentially
already happened because of the time lag
that it takes for us to actually
interpret the those actions so that
energy is needed immediately and it
could be that because of the lag in the
system you know upregulating uh energy
production that's where creating becomes
important in in in a network as you
activate it then you would probably
start to see uh locally if you could
meas you know measure it with say carbon
13 metabolism or something like you
could have a radio tracer on your on
your lactate and you could see that your
asites which make your lactate for your
neurons um will probably increase
production because your neurons are more
active in that area they're going to
require more energy they've used up
their phosphocreatine system and then
the asites locally are going to produce
more lactate none of it's going to
accumulate because it's getting used but
flux through the system is probably
increasing and this is potentially why
people have looked a lot at lactate as a
supplement or as a medication or therapy
for various aspects of a brain injury
and uh brain damage I don't want to go
to this into too much detail because I
covered a whole episode in season one
episode 10 uh all on a paper that that
you led with Dr Federica conti and
myself and some other folks as well on
what we know exactly regarding
supplementation and nutrition for brain
injury so this is concussions cbis and
things like that so you can go and watch
that whole episode and download that
whole grade for all those details there
but in that paper I remember we had a
very short section regarding lactate
yeah and what do we know about lactate
for concussions and stuff like that and
so before you answer that I want to set
the stage just a tiny bit um you can
feel free to maybe double tap on Crea a
little bit here since we we brought it
up but I think it's really important you
have I've seen you give the best
explanation I've ever seen of what a
concussion actually is and what it is
not M and so maybe just quickly tell us
uh your egg
analogy and uh and then that'll help
explain a little bit of why maybe these
things and do or don't work for there so
um how does a concussion actually work
today's episode is sponsored by momentus
momentus makes the highest quality
supplements on the market period many of
you know me and you know that but I do
not trust the vast majority of
supplement companies and for good reason
many Studies have shown that anywhere
between 10 to up to 40% of supplements
have accidental contaminants intentional
alterations mislabeling or other serious
issues but momentus is different I
literally spent years vetting the
company their products and leadership
team before personally officially
partnering with them in 2023 every
single one of momentus this products is
third-party tested to ensure quality and
many are even NSF certified if for sport
now while I love all of their products
the ones I use the most both personally
and with my clients are what I call the
big three and these are the omega-3 fish
oil creatine and newly improved whey
protein formula these three supplements
have fantastic data supporting their
benefits and they have been shown to be
very safe across basically all
populations of people young old men
women Etc now nobody has to use
supplements and I hope you never feel
pressured to do so but if you're
interested in supplements it's important
that you get them from the highest
quality providers so that's why I stick
exclusively to momentus if you'd like to
give momentus to try go to liv.com
perform to get 20% off your order again
that's live mous.com perform to get 20%
off to zoom out for a second I think one
of the reasons why we have really failed
to produce consistent therapies or repr
uble therapies for concussions is
because we don't study them properly and
we don't study them properly because we
don't understand them properly hard to
fix when you can't Define exactly and so
what is normally done or when people
think about a concussion and if you read
papers you'll still see this um
consistently experts in the field
talking about
it you you'll hear something like the
slos effect um or you know you imagine a
head getting bashed and then like the
brain banging around inside the skull
like hitting one side of hitting one
side of the skull then banging and
hitting the other side that's what they
call a contra coup injury which is
basically you see some injury on the
opposite side from from where the impact
occurred the brain
is you know it's mainly fat and water
and it is then surrounded by fluid and
it's inside uh Solid box and that fluid
is full of salt that fluid is full of
salt if you take a solid box full of
water even if it's got something very
fragile inside and you shake it really
hard that fragile thing does not bang
against the sides because the water is
Right buffers it or the you know the CSF
of the the fluid I saw you do this it
was the one of the coolest things I've
ever seen you took an egg and you put it
in a jar with salt water I don't
remember the concentration you put it in
oh it's was just like normal normal
sting yeah and you you know screwed the
top of a ball jar or whatever it was and
you shook the living crap out of the egg
and the yolk didn't break yeah at all no
cuz it's not hitting anything no it's
smashed it stays right in the it stays
right in the middle I in that moment I
went I what like everything because I
had said that always I did not know that
until you showed me that yeah not me but
you're were showing other people and I
was like wow so if if you could while
I'm shaking it image the jar what you
would see is you would see
distortions um along the surface of the
egg yolk inside inside this jar so there
are distortions so the egg instead of
being a perfect circle turns into an
oval it's not smashing against the wall
it's just being just stored in and it's
being um accordioned exctly squished and
and pulled back apart right so how we
generally study concussions is the other
version of of the egg experiment which I
also showed which is that you have your
your egg yolk in your solution and you
leave a big chunk of air in the top of
the jar you shake that immediately it
turns into salad dressing right
immediately you disperse that egg Yol
throughout the liquid that's how we
normally study concussion but what
happens um if you then look at where
injury is in people who've had
concussions so like you look at
individuals who have uh CTE right they
probably have some ongoing history of
concussions it's happened multiple times
if you look at where the injury has
accumulated it's not at the surface of
of the brain it's not the brain bang
against the skull What's happen
is that these distortions like waves of
energy that are transferred through the
brain is at the interfaces of different
parts of the brain so particularly the
interfaces between the gray matter on
the outside and the white matter
underneath it's connective tissue yeah
they're tearing the connector yeah so
right at the usually right at the base
of the sulai so you think about the
brain is really wrinkly right those are
the gy the the sort of the diots in
between those wrinkles the sulai at the
base of those that's where you tend to
see uh injury and it's because you have
uh tissues of different densities where
then the Distortion travels at different
rates so then you create this shearing
effect at those interfaces and then
that's right and if the shearing effect
is very large you can rip axons you
create direct direct axonal injury um if
it's a blast wave then obviously you're
not directly shearing anything but you
still you still seem to injure those
same areas because the energy wave is
transferring through the brain at at
different rates and so that's where the
injur accumulates out at those
interfaces so then how do things like
creatine and lactate help do they work
at all and if so how I've been uh really
excited about the potential for lactate
in traumatic brain injury and and that
uh excitement aligns very similar to
with
ketones um but people have been talking
about them for a long time and I'm still
waiting for some good some good human
studies I've been probably talking about
it for a decade online like in front of
people on podcasts and things like that
yeah
so I I believe that they could be
beneficial but we just haven't seen
really high quality evidence yet however
now that's clear you haven't seen
evidence that shows they don't work
either stud just aren't being done no no
and if if I were to get a significant
concussion or TBI like I'm going
straight to the keton Esters because I
believe that there's a high chance of
benefit with low risk anybody who's like
I don't have a randomized control trial
to tell you that that's the case but you
know I think it could if it was my brain
that's what I would do as an mdphd in
brain health this is what you would do
infer that for what you will folks uh
part of it is that it's essentially
providing some kind of metabolic
substrate in an area of the brain where
there is impaired metabolism so one of
the consistent responses you see to an
acute brain injury and again Strokes
cardiac arrest traumatic brain injuries
is what we call Energy failure so
there's this uh gap between energy
requirements and energy Supply because
you have dysfunctional
mitochondria ketones and lactate can
kind of bypass some of that and seem to
be um less uh Le less energy
energetically expensive or they're more
energetically efficient in terms of
generating ATP like the effect is small
but in that kind of setting a small
effect um may you know may be enough to
help to help minimize injury there's
also going to be some other signaling
effects that that could that could be
beneficial um like both lactate and
ketones have a whole range of other um
anti-inflammatory um neurotrophic kind
of effect so so lactate seems to help
and Ketone seem to help drive an
increase in production in bdnf brain
deriv neurotrophic factor which could
help uh recovery so beyond their effect
on um your metabolism they may have have
these other Downstream uh effects as
well but another reason why this is
important is that in the acute uh injury
setting the brain may become relatively
uh insensitive to glucose or glucose
uptake decreases so um but that doesn't
seem to be the case because the the
transporter is different and both
ketones and lactate go in through the
monoc carboxilate Transporters which
aren't necessarily affected in that
state so some of it could be that
particularly ketones might be more um uh
metabolic efficient in terms of energy
production but also they maybe more
likely to get into the brain in the
setting of of an acute injury to help
support are they potentially less
negatively influenced by inflammatory
markers as well um yes potentially
although I mean it kind of depends on
what's what's going on and how they're
getting
in I don't naturally associate physical
structural damage with metabolic
problems MH what's the connection here
why is it if I have a structural tear
this is a case in muscle by the way yeah
that my my brain is well then it's
inflammation it's damage so you need to
give me something that's
anti-inflammatory nids or some other
drug that is going to reduce the
inflammation or you need to give me
something that's going to repair the
structure DHA fish oil like some
structural thing yeah why are we seeing
and having to deal with and why are
metabolic issues so prevalent glucose
disregulation things like that and then
why is energetic the solution when we
have a physical structural
tear so one of the reasons why you have
impaired glucose metabolism is because
of the inflammatory response and a
normal inflammatory response creates
peripheral insulin resistance in order
to divert glucose to the immune system
in order to in order to respond so
because it has to have energy the immune
system has to get energy as well so that
that that's a good thing in order to to
generate a normal immune response but
can then cause issues in other tissues
because they become insulin resistant
driven by the inflammatory
response the direct Metabolic Effect of
injury is due to the changes that happen
at the cell or in in the nerves in
response to that injury so if it's um
say like a direct shearing effect or um
you know even in concussions where you
haven't um fully sheared neurons you may
have stretched them um and you may have
vascular changes that impair the ability
to deliver oxygen to those tissues and
in all of those settings you can get
essentially a hyper stimulation of those
neurons so they start to fire a bunch
when you get this hypers stimulation of
of neurons um and you see you can see
this with low oxygen States or with you
know acute sort of stretching if you
sort of acutely stretch the neurons they
increase their firing rate that creates
a large production of what we call
excitatory um neurotransmitters things
like glutamate which are the yeah the
most common one but there there are
there are others that then starts this
sort of wave of increase in signaling
you then essentially hyper stimulate the
downstream neurons you get these big
shifts uh in calcium um within the cell
and then that calcium impairs
mitochondrial function and at very high
levels can actually uh stimulate um what
we call the mitochondrial permeability
transition which is essentially the
mitochondria saying I can't take anymore
and then that's that then triggers cell
death so it's essentially an over
stimulation which can be driven either
by low oxygen or stretching um which
then sort of creates this Cascade that
impairs mitochondrial function you
mentioned calcium again that was also
the third part of our uh criteria we
talked about earlier right like that
having that third issue so I want to ask
more about that but let me see if I can
summarize what you just said quick in
the case of a brain injury you're going
to immediately have some sort of
inflammatory response which is a great
thing right the whole point of the
inflammatory response is to let your
immune system know we need to divert
attention and start physically
mechanically repairing collagen and
whatever else is there right
unfortunately those immune cells require
energy and so you have to then divert
glucose to them yeah and the best way to
divert glucose to them is to block it
from going other places yes right now in
this shortterm thing we've basically
given other areas diabetes yeah right
like we made them insulin resist istant
on purpose so that we can focus our
glucose to the immune cells the immune
FS cells then show up to the place of
injury this is all a good thing but
because of that we're going to start
running into in fact we could also be
dealing with tears and damage to the
actual the membrane of the cells right
themselves could be physically torn
which then is going to allow things
coming in and out of the cell that we
don't want and we have like calcium yeah
and having other problems with that
that's the normal process if we were to
then go take copious amounts of say
anti-inflammatories at that stage and
this is probably one of the reasons why
they don't do this m right um we are
probably going to run into issues
because we're blocking that natural
process right so we want some sort of
I'm presuming
inflammation uh immediately but probably
not super excessive yes but not small
yeah either right by the way I'm
guessing all this because this is
exactly how it works in bone and muscle
yeah so tell me when I start to deviate
here right I'm I'm literally guessing so
I I'll jump in just quickly to say that
um in general in in brain injury
everybody's thought that these
inflammatory responses to injury are a
bad thing and we should try and um try
and prevent them and so far that that
has generally failed and actually there
are some therapies you know nothing
that's you know available right now but
there are some therapies that seem to
augment some of the initial responses to
injury inflammatory response to injury
so like in a minute it looks worse but
actually that then ends up resulting in
Improvement longer term there are
Cascades of drugs that pre-dose Pro
pro-inflammatory cyto kindes and whole
Co and then give them to you like give
an exaggerated yeah inflammatory
response in in again another tissue I'm
not surprised it's in sameon bone or in
the brain so once we get past that the
issue then becomes if that stays around
too long and now we're starting to
damage my Andria and now we're having an
issue with regulating energy and that's
why then providing energetic support so
that the cell can stay alive right if
that cell now in the case of the cell
we're talking about the brain cell runs
out of energy then we're going to die
right and so it's a hard time managing
energy and this is why probably
initially in the case of an acute injury
we want to maintain temperature yes
right that's I know that's one thing we
covered uh a little bit in the paper but
I know you spend a lot of time on
because of this process right when
things get really really hot
metabolism has a hard time hanging on
right so things get
overheated managing blood glucose in
general so that this curve is normal and
then at that point providing energenic
support yeah so those were kind of the
three big areas for in the acute setting
um where if you were to actually have a
real injury and you were to get
treatment in hospital like that's
particularly temperature and glucose are
probably the two things are going to pay
attention to most right yeah if were in
an IC like a neuro IU because you had
you had a significant uh traumatic brain
injury then glucose regulation and therm
regulation are known to be critically
important I think in the we kind of
hypothesize that in much less severe
injuries these things are still relevant
so we should think about them there
haven't been a ton of trials in that
area because they're hard to do but it
kind of makes sense that you know just
because you don't have a massive injury
doesn't mean that those things aren't
important for you know quote unquote
just a concussion compared to you know a
major brain trauma what about things
like at home brain tests so there
whether these are uh Technologies where
you can test cognitive function maybe
not I doubt there's any at home
concussion tests that you can do um no
so most most concussion
tests they're yeah generally require
either um some kind of Baseline
cognitive function test so there's
things like the um the impact test uh
the the military have have their own
version of this um there's other tests
that are probably more sensitive to
concussions called the like the king
devic uh test which is basically you
have to read off uh a complex grid of
numbers and letters that kind of like
overlap if you can't read them properly
but you need like you need a baseline
score and you need the same person to
kind of administer it um you also see uh
there are some some uh available devices
where you can measure changes in event
related potentials so uh the electrical
signal that you get if you you know show
somebody an auditory or visual stimulus
um that seem to be pretty good
predictors of like there's actually been
an effect of a concussion and then
recovery but all of this kind of
requires some kind of specialist to be
involved usually um uh more broadly in
terms of in terms of uh cognitive
function what's interesting is that
there aren't a ton of easily available
cognitive function test that you can
like just do at home and do repeatedly
there are some apps and things that kind
of have some of this stuff built in but
it's difficult to St difficult to
standardize um one
uh depending on if you have if you have
say access to some kind of healthc care
provider there are um nice companies
like kayos which give a bunch of
standardized cognitive function tests
you can do at home on a desktop a lot of
um neurologists and neuroscientist use
something like that um I think um the
main cognitive function test that I know
of that anybody can do at home for free
um and is validated is actually U it's
been put online by a charity that I work
with uh in the UK called food for the
brain and they have a a validated online
cognitive function test that includes
measures of um executive function
working memory and processing speed and
you can just like go on their website
and you can just do it and you can track
it over time the and we're we we
currently have a database of more than
half a million people who've taken it
and dozens of thousands of them also
have done lifestyle questionnaires about
sleep and all those kind of things we
talked about so we're in the process of
doing a lot of research from that
database like right at the beginning
we've just sort of be be given access to
be able to do some of that but people
can do that test uh I will say that in
terms of function test it's one of the
ones that has the biggest learning
effect on the second attempt just
because of the way this test is
structured um so if you're going to do
it and you want to like track things
over time I would do it a couple of
times in succession so like you know it
and then use the second or third time as
your Baseline and then track and then
track it over time um but there are
there are a number of people now in this
space because right I can now go to
Quest or lab corop and I can get
whatever blood test I want but I can't
get a really good well validated um
multi-dimensional cognitive function
test that something that you know we and
other people are working on any other
Technologies uh consumer based EG things
that um you you can or cannot mention
the exact products if you'd like but
just where does that field stand I know
that there's
probably half a dozen or more that
immediately come to mind um some of them
s in the front of my head some in my
ears some back place like walk me
through again you can SP specifics if
you want or not but the general lay land
of at home home based EEG
technology I think it's an area where
there's a ton of Promise um it's just
figuring out that's never a good start
no but in a I think in a in a good so I
guess the short answer is is there
anything that gives you everything you
would want right now probably not um
however with very simple EEG devices um
and there are some that are set up in
earphones so I think the one that's um
that I I know is most
widely available or at least will be
soon is is is this company called
neurable um the one the frontal EEG like
Muse is something that people were going
to be familiar with and actually there
were versions of the Muse that have the
sensors around the ear as well some of
the why does it matter if it's in the
front of the forehead versus the ear it
depends and it depends on what you're on
what you're looking
at with some of my collaborators we're
looking at different um EG frequencies
and people have heard of like alpha beta
theta Delta and the different uh like
the relative uh frequencies and power of
these different um fre so like even
within a frequency band uh people will
have different average frequencies and
then uh the the sort of the total
amplitude of the wave is is the power
and the the your mean frequency and
Power in those different frequency bands
relates to different aspects of
cognitive function so uh certain aspects
of alpha seem to predict um say learning
speed for Lear learning a second
language and some other aspects of
cognitive function um some companies
have created like Focus metrics so like
you can tell when your brain is focused
that's either based on um uh certain
measures of alpha or sometimes they have
like a alpha plus beta divided by Delta
plus Theta or some kind of ratio of the
different frequencies and that stuff is
is pretty good the problem is that each
individual company kind of focuses on
one thing right so you're using it for
neuro neuro feedback in kind of like a
meditation type um uh setting yeah or
you're using it to kind of tell when
you're focusing well and then your focus
is starting to drop off and maybe it's
time to to take a break I think that you
could get a lot more uh and and broader
information about somebody's cognitive
function over time with some of these
Technologies even even simple setups but
just nobody's really done that yet so
kind of selling Focus or selling
meditation
that stuff's great like don't get me
wrong I think it's an important start
but I think there's a lot more that
could be done if we had the right
information and we sort of track in
people over time yeah so the only well
perhaps not maybe the only but the
largest consideration there for the
consumer is just that last Point yeah so
it's going to be at least that I'm aware
of that you're aware of any consumer
faced product there is going to have one
particular aspect of cognitive function
but it will almost certainly not test
nor train and help you evaluate other
aspects of cognitive function function
which is not their fault this is a more
than small technological
yeah really yeah challenging the calcium
question yes right so what does calcium
have to do with this entire project why
does it matter if calcium influx is
happening or this um ayot toxicity with
glutamate what's that got to do with it
and then does calcium work then as a
supplement I can take to enhance
cognitive function to deal with brain
andry walk us through the story with
calcium so
I I think this is another area where
um the brain and muscle kind of tell a
similar story right we know that
muscular and the Heart Right the
muscular contraction is driven by
cycling of um calcium right and a lot of
signaling processes including
mitochondrial function and then the
transfer of um information um across
cells in the brain is driven by waves of
calcium and so that then you know opens
and closes um different channels it you
know activates or deactivates different
entic processes it regulates bondal
function just like it does um in in the
muscles so when you have large you know
excessive or unregulated um influx of
calcium into a
cell you know one of the prototypical
downstream effects is mitochondrial
dysfunction and eventually lighten
mitochondrial death and you
mitochondrial death you essentially have
cell totally totally that's what you're
going to see is sell um
so when you then think about like
calcium as a supplement obviously th
those those two things don't go directly
together uh you can't take more calcium
and then have better regulation of um
energetics in the brain unfortunately
because it's just a lot more complicated
than that but I think this is where some
other things come into play like we know
that like so vitamin D is really is
really important
for cognitive function one of its Ro I
mean it's essentially a steroid hormone
but one of its roles is in the
regulation of calcium so that you know
that it could be playing a role there we
know like magnesium and calcium play
together and often sort of like playing
off one another we know that magnesium
is really critical there so some of
these other factors that we know are
important for cognitive function may be
playing a role through regulation of
calcium but if you was going to take
more calcium um it's unfortunately it's
not going to just end up in your brain
and improve cognitive function unless
you know for whatever reason you were
calcium deficient which is relatively
rare usually it's other factors um
vitamin K status you know other things
that that that are playing a big role
there yeah I mean uh what's the RDA for
calcium thousand milligrams a day like
something like that right you don't
rarely see people or you don't often see
people it might be like 7 or 800
milligrams it's not that much okay maybe
see lesson yeah pretty I mean a smidgens
of broccoli
and it's like some Dairy like you're
probably there Prett you eat any dairy
you'll hit your idea of calcium yeah
you're not going to smash that up there
and also seems to be one of the the
minerals particularly that doesn't like
to be outside of its window yeah in the
sense that if you get a little bit high
in magnesium particularly if you really
physically active that's probably okay
yeah in fact like often times that's
good yeah uh you don't want to do that
with calcium no and it's even more
tightly it's even more tightly regulated
because it's essentially a trigger for
so many and like it's how so many
biological processes are regulated your
heart will stop yeah so you needed to be
your brain will stop like it's not a
good thing yeah way low way high so it's
not one and for those cases I mean
thinking back over your
career how many times you think you've
recommended calcium supplementation
based on blood work or things like that
I think the only time you routinely
recommended it was in like osteoporotic
older individuals but you were taking it
with vitamin D and we were trying to You
Know cover some other bases as well so
like just giving like Calum on its own I
don't think I've ever recommended yeah
so not in your performance enhancement
with your athletes not in your practice
as a medical doctor none of those things
right I don't think I've ever given it
though so magnesium like ubiquitously
yeah like everybody people down with it
totally and but calcium is probably not
one of the ones so probably not one of
the markers we're going to go after for
either cognitive enhancement or the
brain injury things like that
okay you have said three things thus far
in our conversation that have irritated
probably many
people are you remind them what they are
I am and then I want to see if we can go
for a fourth okay one thing you said was
that things like micro doing
psychedelics and marijuana probably
don't potentially don't necessarily
enhance creativity yeah they certainly
enhance your perception of it but maybe
actually you're not doing better work
you're just high and thinks your stuff
is great when it sucks okay that was
number one whole internet will hate me
for that too the second thing you said
was actually that you're you're fairly
convinced at this point that we can
actually enhance cognitive function
which doesn't sound controversial to
some but for others are going to be
really upset about that and what you
mean by that is General so that is
transferable to other modes of cognitive
function as we just talked about focus
is not the same as executive function
that's not the same as word recall Etc
and that that can be improved and we
laid out various cases for that third
one you said was that in fact
concussions and brain injuries are not
your brain slamming against your skull
um that probably could happen it's
plausible but most likely you have
either temperature or Distortion or
metabolic issue or combinations of us
there fourth one and I've heard you on
records so true or false here you are of
the opinion that dementia and late onset
Alzheimer's not early onset to be clear
are 100% preventable I've never said
100% okay all
right okay I would say so um and this
really at this point shouldn't be
controversial because again Dusty
neurological institutions led by
establishment individuals would say the
same thing um that I would say that so
the the party line is that 45% of
dementia is probably de uh preventable
that's from the lanet commission run by
Gil Livingston and a bunch of experts
across across the world it was just
updated it used to be 40% now it's 45%
they increased the number of risk
factors that they
included I would say it's easily the
majority because there were some things
that they didn't include 60 plus per 70
plus% so other estimates um so say uh
yinu who's at Fudan University and his
group have done a ton of uh modeling and
prediction from large population data
sets they think that somewhere between
you know up to 70 something per of
dementia is preventable if we were able
to address all the different risk
factors that contribute to it okay so
this is an enormous departure yeah from
what the Lexicon right so not only
potentially is it a departure from the
scientific Community but if you were to
walk down the street and just ask people
about first of all they'll call it
Alzheimer's probably right yeah um but
dementia I don't know anyone who thinks
that this is anything besides this just
happens with age or it's like cancer
where it's just a bad luck of the draw
potentially some people might think oh
it's you know if I drink a lot of
alcohol but I don't think many people
think it's anything besides those ones
so not only are you saying that that is
not the case yeah but it is in large
part call it even 40% is impressive but
probably more realistically 70 plus perc
of dementia is extinguishable so
two-part question is this a prevention
issue or is this a reversal
there are certainly some people out
there who who working with individual
clinical cases have said they have seen
what they feel is reversal of
Alzheimer's disease that I'm still not
hard like because once you've reached
that point of significant atch Fe and
significant pathology it's very
difficult to um restore function and or
you know reverse or structur
structurally but then also to respond to
some of the things that we know uh
improve cognitive function so this is
all this is all vention case studies
maybe things like that that like in
terms of reversal demena is the same
case or just Alzheimer's most of this is
focused on Alzheimer's but some people
will say you know in in certain cases of
front temporal Dementia or Louis body
dementia they've seen significant
improvements in cognitive function and
it's by generally addressing the same
things but I I wouldn't come here and
promise reversal but I do think
prevention um there's you know massive
potential slowing down onset slowing
down progression is certainly thing yeah
we we'll talk about that separate I'll
keep it going I'll bring you back to
that so there's reversing they're
stopping the progression and they're
stopping it from happening yes so okay
continue on with the prevention piece so
um and I think all of all of this is
essentially um all of this is connected
and and the same risk factors apply
essentially across the board uh
regardless of where you're trying to
intervene it probably just gets harder
the further you go along so when uh they
classify them in the lanet commission
report
they sort of classify them by stages of
life so early life the most significant
uh modifiable risk factor is is
education so the more years of education
you have the lower your risk of later
dementia and uh then late life cognitive
stimulus also becomes important and uh
that's that's been shown again in meta
analyses by Professor y use group and is
Incorporated in into this lantic
commission
report so I think that's a good place to
start because it fits with my worldview
that stimulus is really important that's
always good and so um and you have by
the way you and Josh have a paper Open
Access paper we'll fully link to that in
the show notes so you guys can go fully
read that but yeah continue on if you
want to read this whole breakdown that
paper will be up yeah so you can kind of
hear think about this idea and again
it's sort of driven by that same idea
that stimulating to like the function of
a tissue is directly proportional to the
stimulus applied to it the liver is the
same the immune system is the same
muscles the same and so when you look at
trajectories of cognitive function
across the lifespan um and there were
you know multiple M analyses and a lot
of this has to be observational but what
you see is that um those who have more
years of education they have a higher
peak of cognitive function and that's
you you spend more time you know
devoting more resources to enhancing
cognitive function I got I'm sorry to
cut you off for like the fourth time but
I have to linger on that point it makes
intuitive sense that the more time
modern education than hands cognitive
function I have right but that's not
what you just said what you just said
was you reach a higher Peak
yeah I I hope people are sinking in on
what the heck that that means right we
all can progress we can improve but
getting to a higher total maximum Peak
is really it's not the same as just
increasing in speed and it's what's
stunning me about this and I'll keep
going back to it you will see the same
thing with bone mhm right the maximum
bone density you get is going to be
predicted by what you did between ages
10 to 14 yeah now the rate of increasing
is like pretty much ubiquitous like up
and down is the same but determining how
high that Peak is is all about what you
do in that window so I'm I'm just like
so stunned right now that uh I knew the
increase right I could certainly would
have said hey would you improve
cognitive function like yes if you train
but I I would was not anticipating you
would say that that the height of that
Peak is going to be determined by that
as well yeah cuz you're going to deal
with that the downside the rest of your
life exactly yeah and so you know a lot
of other things go into that but you
generally see that people that the
higher your uh so if you think about
Peak cognitive function which depending
on what it what cognitive function
you're looking at and how you measure it
the peak is going to be somewhere
between 20 and 30 years old and it
generally an individual Peaks sometimes
sometime around the time they finish
formal education right so all that kind
of lines up to say that the more time
you spend on that the higher the peak
and at that Peak the peak is higher in
those who on average who have longer
education across multiple methods of
testing cognition cogni function yeah
and right you have to talk about the
fact that you know different people get
access to longer periods and like so all
of that plays right social economic
status plays a big role and access plays
a big role here right but I think in the
last commission report they said that 5%
of dementia was preventable if just like
everybody got adequate yeah got adequate
education and the reason for that is so
if we then imagine some trajectory of
congressed
decline um that occurs in everybody on
and like the rate is is different and we
can we can change the rate of decline
but if all you did was educate people
more early in life they would have a
higher Peak the rate of decline would be
the same but they'd reach the point of
dementia later right because they've
started from a higher Peak the same rate
of decline means they reach dementia
later and you know maybe they die of
something else first and they never get
dementia so like that's that's how that
then happens we also quickly Define age
there early and age is that like
adolesence is that high school is that
all of it just kind of ly in terms of
what uh you just said that that the
higher more education we give them early
in life oh yeah so this is just like the
traditional education years right so
like you go up not a specific hey
between age five and eight is the most
no so it's it's just total years of
education so did you do complete High
School like bachelor's degree graduate
school like is sort of a roughly linear
relationship okay and then um there are
several studies that show that late life
ative um engagement or stimulus and
they've measured it with like how often
you go like you read books and go to
museums and all these kinds of things or
they've done it through like how
cognitively stimulating is your work
that then also slows or is associated
with a slower rate of Decline and also a
slower uh uh or a lower risk of dementia
so there was one study they actually
included and sort of stole the forest
plot from it and they included it in the
Lan commission report they had early
life education and then they had how
cognitively stimulating your job was and
what they saw was that people who had
more early life education um and but not
a stimulating job and cognitiv
stimulating job and people who had less
early life education but a cognitively
stimulating job later in life they had
about the same risk of dementia so you
can offset um a lower education early in
life with more cognitive stimulation
later in life the lowest risk was
obviously those who had both but um it's
yes there's a huge amount of benefit you
get from that early stimulation through
education but it's not like you're you
now written in stone like this is your
destiny I have a higher risk of dementia
if you didn't get that because there's
lots of evidence that suggest that
stimulation either through your job or
other things will then slow that decline
later in life so so you can still do
something about it later it's so
interesting because you're like halfway
between muscle and bone now yeah such
that the muscle you develop as a child
has almost no bearing m on how much
muscle you can develop if you start
lifting weights for the first time at 50
your rate of increase in muscle growth
will be the same yeah as if you lifted
weights when you were 10 or not or
basically like that so in there that
case like earlier development has very
little bearing on progression like so
how the rate of
increase that said bone is the opposite
like whatever you get basically as a kid
in large part is is going to determine
where you're at there so you have this
Halfway House of where muscle is not
relying upon you know when you're a kid
bone almost entirely and now what you're
saying is like brain is a little bit of
both you got either one right you can do
it early in life you can do it late in
life obviously both is great or worst
case here and and I would have to
imagine I don't know if you actually
know the numbers here but the folks that
were the double dipping on the bad side
MH so no education and low cognitive
demanding job I have to imagine their
rates of Alzheimer and uh dementia as
well as progression is probably the most
aggressive there by by an order not
maybe maybe not a magnitude but some
fold yeah so in in this um uh in this
paper was published in the in the bmj a
few years ago they like that was your
reference group and then everybody else
just did just did better right just
2.0's 2.7 yeah just doubling over there
okay so I guess if you had a great
childhood education tremendous don't
rest on your laurels continue to
challenge cognitive demanding whatever
that may be if you didn't though you
still can regain much of that by doing
something just don't use that to have
your mind numbing
job um as where there so it is in either
case largely preventable the I think the
the departure here is um early onset
Alzheimer's yeah is is a different ball
game entirely here right we I don't want
to spend too much time here but now
you're probably looking at probably
opposite like 70 plus percent is maybe
even higher is genetic and bad draw here
so so I think just just to finish the
the the first piece like we think about
life stages and think about the life
stages of risk factors then um in the
middle of Life a lot of what they're
talking talking about is body
composition physical activity um smoking
alcohol you know all the stuff that
we've talked about already in terms of
if we eliminated those we could
eliminate yeah you know the related
dementia and then one thing that we
haven't talked about before or at least
not related to this is sensory inputs so
that's some of the late life risk
factors they talk about obviously brain
trauma is another one in
midlife yeah but no sensory to like
vision and hearing yeah so there's now a
pretty good body of evidence suggests
that if you have cataracts you have a
higher risk of dementia that Dem that
risk is reversed if you have cataract
surgery if you have hearing loss like
presbycusis as you get older you have a
higher risk of um dementia that is
reversed particularly in high-risk
people uh if you get hearing aids so if
you start to lose a sense right and a
lot of people just like I'm going to
battle through because you know I don't
want to have a hearing aid or whatever
oh do don't do that you know if you
start to have hearing loss get a hearing
aid because that's going to be
associated with a lower risk of dementia
so making sure you're still getting
those sensory inputs into the brain uh
remains really critical so don't lose
your sense of smell don't lose your
vision don't lose your hearing probably
in the I'm going to guess 50 to 60 year
range like if you start getting in that
age window and you start seeing
precipitate declines in any of those
functions and you want to reverse that
as quickly as you possibly can um
because of what you've been saying all
day yeah if you can't hear stimuli
doesn't go in there then that part of
your brain presumably dies it makes
perfect sense right you're not using
those networks anymore so they're going
to decline but then all you know
everything else they're connected to is
going to be affected as I assume the
same thing is true with Pro perception
in terms of balance things like that
right so make sure that you continue to
train balance work on balance I think
this is a pretty easy story to tell for
exercise in nature
yeah right exercising in the outdoor
like exercising inside in the gym is
great but now you're outside you're
going up and down you're seeing
different things hearing smelling like
so on and so forth differing light
exposures like the effect of say seeing
green spaces on you autonomic nervous
system regulation or there's there's a t
yeah there's a ton of different ways
that that that could okay
so I'm on board there um it's highly
preventable you said this earlier as
well you talked about exercise a bunch
MH um this was one of the more stunning
Parts about our earlier conversation
when you said and I I'm I'm stupified
that I never made this connection I've
said this a thousand times a thousand
plus thousands of times and like I never
really grasp the fact that when you
exercise you're going to have
neurological
neuroplasticity nerve nerve nerve but
then the actual structure of the brain
and I promise we would I wanted to come
back there so here we are coming back to
it it's like the second time I've
actually come back to a topic I said I
wanted to come back to but I want you to
explain this to me about how it's
actually what what aspects of the what
areas of the brain physically are
improved by exercise does itpe determine
or does it depend on the type of
exercise is strength training different
um do we know any details about the
exercise is it a certain amount of sets
or reps or Styles like what do we know
um so what do I do and how does it
actually help and then the last part
about that
is is there a a law of hey I didn't
start soon enough yeah so now it's too
late all right so give me the jazz on
how lifting weights makes my brain what
do you call it like bigger bigger
muscles bigger brains more bigger more
brainia more bigger more brainia there
you go I've heard you say that before
um so a good place to start is the the
first ever study
I think that was done that showed that
you could increase the size of a certain
part of of the brain in humans was with
an exercise intervention was published
in 2011 exercise for the win I'm telling
you folks exercise scientists run
science you just don't like to admit it
um so this published in PN in 2011 and
what they did is oh that recent yeah oh
wow yeah so there was the so like before
then we knew that so if you just looked
at brains of people who'd recently died
you could see that there were certain
areas of the brain that were there was
some neurogenesis particularly the
dentate gyus at hippocampus but to
actually physically see an increase in
size of a part of the brain this is the
hippocampus which is generally just
thought to get smaller and smaller over
time that hadn't that hadn't been seen
before yeah hard hard to do in humans
yeah and so the other side of that is
that we don't know if there's more
neurons being generated we know it's
bigger right so this is like it could be
clear it could be exra Matrix there's a
whole bunch of things that go into that
but that doesn't necessarily matter we
can we see improvements in in uh brain
uh structure and volume with an exercise
intervention so what they did in this
study individuals in their 60s and 70s
they had them do a walking program 40
minutes three times a week for a year
that's it brisk walking and that was
enough to significantly improve or
increase the size of the hippocampus
these are non- exercisers these are non-
exercises yeah and they sort of like
worked their way up to a certain
intensity and they did it for 40 minutes
three times a week for a year the
increases in size of the hippocampus
correlated with improvements in V2 Max
which also correlat with improvements in
or increases in production of bdnf brain
derived neurotrophic Factor so in a s
sedentary population right we know we
can see improvements in in uh the
structure of the brain with with
exercise with aerobic
exercise what was interesting is that in
this study they didn't necessarily see
significant improvements in cognitive
function they saw improvements in
structure but function didn't
necessarily truck with
it part of this is probably an intensity
piece so there was a very recent study
that looked at um different levels of
intensity of exercise aerobic exercise
again and structure and function of of
hippocam of the hippocampus so again so
now we're thinking about memory related
uh tests and they found the greatest
benefit in individuals doing high
intensity exercise training it was
essentially the Norwegian 4x4 Pro like 4
minutes it's at you know uh 75 to 80%
Max V like V2 Max um uh heart rate sorry
and they saw maintenance of structure of
volume of the hippocampus compared to
control groups where it kind of where
those decreased and M and improvements
in in cognitive function they think
related to the area of the brain so some
um aerobic activity of any kind in
people who are sedentary if it improves
their cardiovascular fitness then you're
going to see improvements in brain
structure to see correlated improvements
in brain function intensity is probably
going to be important they in that study
they're generating a ton of lactate
right whereas they weren't in that
original Walking study right so that
that could be that could be one one way
wi again so um in general what you see
across multiple studies is that the gray
matter of the brain so now we're talking
the the outer cortex and hippocampus
primarily seems to be benefited by
aerobic exercise and in general arobic
exercise seems to be associated with
improvements in memory right again the
hippocampus is is is really important
there you if we're thinking about the
amount that you have you have to do it's
essentially going to be you know two or
three times a week some kind of activity
that is improving your cardiovascular
fitness wherever you've started from
right but probably at least once a week
doing something that's very intense
right some kind of some kind of Sprint
type or high high intensity interval
training at least that's what sort of
aligns with the literature
in terms of resistance exercise you see
benefits in different areas of the brain
so resistance exercise seems to
primarily benefit the white matter which
kind of sits between the cortex and the
deep brain and right that's where you
have your mated axons the fast
connections um like that's the hypers
speed zone the hypers speed zone is the
transfer of information from the brain
to the body and throughout the brain and
uh so we actually just published a
review paper talking about the studies
where they've done a resistance training
intervention compared to a control group
and then looked at brain structure over
time and this is what you see is
Improvement either improvements in the
wipe in the white matter or prevention
of decline of the structure of of the
white matter um and then that's also
associated with um improvements in
cognitive function particularly with
resistance training executive function
so like prefrontal cortex function so
different areas of the brain affected by
different types of exercise which then
associated with different improvements
in cognitive function the uh minimum
effective dose um seat for like
sustained Improvement seems to be two
sessions a week um like super standard
six to eight exercises covering the
whole body for three sets of 8 to 12
reps just like the most basic resistance
training program twice a week for at
least six months and you see significant
improvements in brain structure and
Associated cognitive function so those
are kind of the different ways that
those different exercises kind of come
together then then you get more of like
a Glo if you do both hopefully some kind
of global Improvement ctive function so
it is never been shown I know this but
it would based on all that be reasonable
to presume if I wanted to develop an
exercise program that was specifically
targeted with the primary objective of
keeping my brain as healthy as long as
possible not necessarily my body
composition or muscle or strength or
anything like that um I wanted to do an
exercise program for that one could
theoretically say Okay lift weights a
couple of days a week in exactly what
you mentioned you know five to eight
exercises whole body Yeah couple sets
each yeah that'd be two days a week one
day a week do something that is closer
let's just even say the Norwegian 4x4
that's a great option yeah four minutes
of the highest amount of work people get
mad when you describe this as four
minutes of Max effort are all out you
can't go all out for four minutes but
the the highest amount of work you can
do for four minutes rest for four
minutes and do it again I don't really
think friends like I cannot imagine a
world in which that specificity matter
yeah you don't have to do the for you
could probably do just about any type of
high-intensity endurance conditioning
work and it would probably be the same
but let's just say for Simplicity you
did 4x4 once or twice a week was that
those interventions I think they were
doing it three times a week okay but if
you're doing other aerobic exercise and
and resistance training I think you're
gonna yeah you're probably not going to
need to do like 4x4 three times a week
that Su that's pretty damn hard
especially for six months of time yeah
yeah I'm going to say realistically as
an exercise scientist I'll give you
permission to cut that to two yeah per
week yeah and then maybe one to two or
three sessions a week of the more lower
intensity standard endurance exercise
cardio whether this is even physical
activity walking yeah uh or would they
actually need to do more like 50 60%
heart rate for that kind of
cardiovascular adaptation so you know
this is that this is the the age-old
question is like it like what's the
exact intensity required to see a
specific adaptation I think that and
it's the same we did a we did a podcast
talking about the 4x4 your podcast on on
my podcast and um then somebody was like
well what if I can't maintain my heart
rate in that zone for that long like
just do yeah right do whatever you can
for four minutes and you right you'll
get better over time and so I think it's
I think it's the same thing yeah like if
it's a if it's a casual stroll you're
probably not getting um an adaptation
but you know equally if if a brisk walk
is hard work for you right then that's
going to be that that that's going to be
a good good place to be yeah this one
roused me up so much because I I get it
people want like specific
numbers but I'm
so resistant to do that because it
doesn't actually matter usually yeah
it's a it's a rough concepts of where
you're at so if those numbers help you
great but something like that um here's
the reality don't think that your brain
all of a sudden won't adapt yeah if you
do half that yeah yeah if you did one
day of lifting one day of intervals and
a couple of days of walking it's better
than the zero oh yeah it's a lot better
yeah right so you don't have to hit that
minimum number to get any effect
whatsoever right probably getting closer
to that Final Destination but if that
takes you six months or six years to get
to where you can handle that that being
that little three you know protocol we
talked about it's fine yeah like get
there eventually and and you'll probably
get um much of the benefit which which
is
great this actually answers a big
question that I have dealt with a lot
you and I actually have a a paper
together again that you led where we
found physical strength predicted I
think it was 5% yeah of cognitive
function right and I'll I'll say that
again like physical strength predicted
5% of cognitive
function I have talked about people have
talked about at length how leg
strength how grip strength grip strength
fires people up right and the common
claim here is like a grip strength is
just a proxy for overall health yeah and
certainly true MH um if you look at
research on folks that have dementia you
will see I think actually one paper
found I can't even think it was UK bank
paper about a half a million people in
it found that I think
30% of Alzheimer's death was explained
by low grip rate yeah right not a small
number and there's a recent study
showing that Frailty preed like precedes
like Alzheimer's by by several years on
average multiple years I imagine right
and right if you're frail you're not
doing all the things that we know
continue to stimulate or support brain
function right so what I want you to
kill and perhaps this is the fifth thing
that'll irritate the internet that we're
going to call is the idea that this
stuff the grip strength leg strength is
exclusively an indirect or a correlation
right of course there's some yeah folks
who are struggling with dementia are
probably also then GNA struggle with
movement and there'll be a backwards
direction right there'll be a causation
but it would kind of be backwards yeah
causation right so and this horrible
idea that strength is only a correlation
to brain health and you just actually
kind of answered the question before
which is like how is it actually caal
but then spell this out as directly as
possible so I can cut this clip and send
it to people every damn time I get told
it's just a correlation technically
people are right a lot of this comes
from epidemiological research
correlation isn't causation um however
there were several studies we just
talked about some where you randomize
some to a resistance training
intervention their strength improves
brain function improves right brain
structure improves and actually related
to the point that you making in that in
one of those studies yes you see
sustained improvements in white matter
structure with two sessions a week but
you got improvements in cognitive
function with just one session a week
right so you don't that these effects
particularly if people aren't doing much
exercise are essentially linear and like
so I
I if you could ask for a more
causal function and structure benefit
and in a dose response yeah so what else
do we that essentially says it's causal
right yeah and people are so depending
on the type of research of course people
are right you you can't tell you can't
tell causation
however what people also don't
necessarily understand is that in a
perfect epidemiological study if you
could account for every confounder and
you know mediating and moderating
relationships what you have left is
causation that is like by Def that is a
definition of causation so yes
epidemiological studies technically
don't show causation but if you could
it's difficult because you don't always
get the variables you want right you can
determine causation from an
epidemiological study that is possible
that's allowed in you know a frequenc
model of Statistics I'll count that as
like 4.5 thing that internet's going to
get mad at
yeah you don't think people understand
basic statistics with that so um right
people have worse physical health right
we know so in the study that we did if
you had higher uh blood blood sugar high
hb1 C you had lower strength but I think
that's also bidirectional right you know
more insulin resistance that's going to
worsen um muscular function but um if we
think about the potential mechanisms by
which this happens you have uh if you're
doing things that improve strength
that's Direct neuromuscular stimulus
we've already talked about the
importance of stimulus the next
important thing is that your skeletal
muscle is your biggest and most
important glucose snc so if we're
thinking about the importance of energy
regulation then your muscle like the
more muscle you have and the more you
move it the greater amount of glucose
you can move through that system and
there I mean this has been done for
decades and decades and decades so your
your skeletal muscle and your physical
activity are two of the best ways to
improve glucose handling and energetic
handling more broadly and then the final
piece is that when you contract your
muscles you release a whole bunch of
stuff right your muscles are organs so
lactate bdnf m c irin uh Lac Fe like
pick your metabolite
cinin like whatever like whatever it is
like pick your favorite metabolite dour
right um we're still discovering like
torine we're still discovering on a like
on a we basis the things that are
released during exercise that have broad
broad benefits so like all of that comes
together to suggest that um yes it's a
bidirectional relationship but by
improving muscular size and strength and
function and those usually go together
but not always depending on you know who
you are um that's there was four or five
if not more different mechanisms that
would directly Rel relate to
improvements in cognitive function and
brain health I I hope that ends the
conversation I'm going to move on
although we could probably have done a
whole conversation just on that but one
little piece here it makes sense to me
energetically based on what you just
describe it makes sense to me from a
neuromuscular perspective that the
strength training Works backwards right
and so the same neurological system that
makes you squeeze your hand together it
starts in your brain keeps alive how
does the white matter what's the stimuli
from exercising muscle cuz it makes
sense when I think about muscle it
doesn't happen this way folks but as a
teaching point if you think about I
lifted some weights the muscles that I
contracted they pulled they got
stretched they contracted they got
damaged again it doesn't happen this way
but I can I can paint that picture in my
head I'm not stretching the tissue yeah
in my brain when I'm lifting weights so
how am I generating more or preserving
my physical tissue outside of the
metabolic and the um the asites and the
nervous system side yes so I think all
of those play play an important role um
for instance we know that as as we age
things like changes in in metabolic
health and white matter structure in the
brain probably better track with
cognitive function than say something
like amalo accumulation in your brain
actually the the trajectory follows more
closely and that's going to be related
to um so so the white Mass trajectory is
going to be related to things like
metabolic health for the for the reasons
we talked about um but I think there's a
direct stimulating effect right as you
are you know the both learning the new
skill of of of like the muscular control
required to uh move uh weight in that
way I think you're directly stimulating
some of those Pathways so Pathways
related to like motor pathways assoc
like white matter Pathways associated
with motor control I think you'll
directly stim ating those which and then
we know as you stimulate those you
offset all those things we talked about
earlier in terms of adaptations that
improve structure and function and then
more broadly I think that's where some
of the um the signaling Pieces come into
play what's interesting is that there is
an overlap in some of the things that
are produced in aerobic exercise versus
um uh resistance training but we do see
region specific effects so it's probably
there's like some some coupling of of
what's going of what's going on like a
specific stimulus plus um the sort of
the hormonal M or the myokines and
things that that are released um and I I
think it's that it's some combination of
that it's really hard to test these
mechanisms in humans and it's actually
also really hard to get rats to do bicep
curls so um squats is easy but yeah yeah
or um because they have like they do
like they do um weighted weighted Wheels
right so it's kind of like a a weighted
Jacobs Ladder kind of thing is what they
do for resistance training in rats um
but I think it's some combination of
those things if you look at this from
the muscle skeletal muscle perspective I
should probably be saying it that whole
I always say muscle skeletal muscle all
right a little bit different it doesn't
require damage yeah there's another
thing that people have this this false
thought of you have to break a muscle
down to grow back which is fundamentally
not only not true but it actually
doesn't happen very often right it's not
generally what's causing muscle damage
it's not causing soreness it's not
causing and it's definitely not the
stimuli to grow M you can simply change
energetics MH and stimulate muscle
growth skeletal muscle growth I can't
see why you couldn't do that in the
brain yeah it's the same thing it
doesn't require a stretch and a damage
yeah all of these adaptations are driven
by an increase in energetic flux right
that's what it is at its most basic
state and then that's what that drives
um neuroplasticity it drives autophagy
it drives you know all these other
regulatory processes that we know um are
involved in aging and reversing those um
and so anything you can do right locally
in muscle improve increasing energetic
flux through aerobic exercise you know
and then the same any stimulus in the
brain you're increasing the amount of
energy that's moving through the system
that acts as a stimulus that then the
same same processes occur is that why
you think those different modes of
exercise produce different actual brain
adaptations I think that's parts of it
yeah um sort of but all of those things
seem to you know dissecting those exact
Pathways hasn't been done but it um if
you think about well you get you get La
you know you do a heavy set of leg press
you release it lactate right um but and
you release a lot of lactate when you do
the 4x4 protocol but you get different
you seem to get different responses in
the brain so it's the the the
combination of of multiple things sort
of coming together all right fascinating
uh we're going to press the button on
more things you're going to irritate the
world
about I don't need the full dive here
give me the the what we used to say in
the '90s and 2000s the reader digest
version I only now recently realize that
kids have no idea what that means no
that analogy now people like the what
like all right tldr tldr well nobody
reads anymore so right you mentioned TOA
MH and amals yeah and for folks that
don't know this story these for many
years have been surrogates or markers of
of would you say brain aging brain
damage or yeah sort of the brain
pathology that's then leads to
Alzheimer's disase right and then
recently some information came out that
um perhaps we'll just leave the person
nameless but one of the prominent
scientists in this area had we'll just
say not necessarily fake data but there
there was some controversy and so I've
seen reactions that are on one side of
the equation of like okay he he just
used a couple of pictures in GRS
scientists do this all the time he
didn't fake data he just kind of got
lazy you submit grants and grants and
grants and you're using a representative
image to show a concept like it's not
that big a deal all the way to ractions
in the other side of equation which is
okay 30 years of research in this area
is all thrown out now yeah
um if you feel like you can't answer
this quickly then that's okay feel free
to pass but uh where at do we know um
should people still be worried about
this Pro because you can test it people
pay to get it tested how much should we
worry about to in relation to brain
health yes so this is a it's a long
question to answer because essentially
it it starts with Alis Alzheimer and his
mentor amo klin in Germany in the
beginning of the 20th century um however
um I think we can say that there has
been this overriding or there's still
the overriding idea that um Alzheimer's
disease is driven by something called
the amid Cascade
hypothesis um amalo precursor protein is
produced in the brain normally it's
really important for neuroplasticity a
whole bunch of things if you if you like
got rid of outs of um AP and amid
entirely basically the brain doesn't
function at all um and but there's one
so of this preor protein gets can get
cut in different ways by these
secretases one version of that um
accumulates to create these sort of waxy
amalo plaques when that happens that
then stimulates the the production of
towel so tow is normally part of the
microtubular Cy skeleton of neurons like
really important for like directing
axons and where they go and how they
connect and it sort of dissociates from
that becomes phosphorated and
accumulates and then that Dam build of
tow is generally Associated as a bad
thing yeah and then that sort of Damages
neurons and that's associated pick your
poison here if you look at sleep yeah
you will see basically an inverse
relationship with sleep efficiency or
Sleep Quality and Tow buildup like you
you could pick this in any realm of
there and and it'd be hard to ignore all
yeah of those papers so um I I
think this certainly plays a role I
think the and there's been an increasing
number of voices that say that there are
other things that have to be playing a
significant role here as well so we've
become really hyperfocused on this one
pathway when this pathway like you said
is triggered by a whole bunch of things
that we know have effects Beyond how it
affects that pathway right we know that
sleep is important regardless of the
fact that if you don't sleep you
accumulate a bit more amalo in the brain
right so and we know that uh towel
accumulates after head trauma but there
are other effects that head trauma has
Beyond its effect on towel so we've kind
of really hyperfocused on this pathway
but there's a bunch of other stuff
that's happening at the same time and I
think we could while we shouldn't throw
the baby out with the bath water because
some of that is certainly playing a role
I think we'll miss um a huge amount of
benefit from uh in people if if we don't
focus on the other things that are going
on at the same time so I think there's
an even though and so there's been some
studies in with amalo where you know a
similar problem you know some issues
with the data maybe some of it was
duplicated or fabricated I think there's
enough evidence to suggest this is
playing a role I just think the role is
probably smaller than we've kind of uh
assumed it to have yeah I mean I'll say
that for you because I'm not in this
field you may have to save face a little
bit but I can only speak this from my
area of Science and I've seen this game
play out where um the funding sources
the national funding sources just start
onslot and probably for good reason
initial papers come out it gets really
exciting and they just put all the
dollars yeah on one particular thing and
this is by my read of the situation from
the outside and this is basically what
happened right and it becomes really
hard with anybody else with an idea or
an approach or a metric to get funding
because they're just throttling it all
on one area and then when information
like this comes out it becomes really
disheartening and upsetting to folks who
got their ideas shut down for yeah
career MH and going we told you to stop
focusing on that and and I think that's
somewhere in the neighborhood of a fair
criticism if people are interested in
this history they should read the book
how not to study a disease by KL harup
which kind of documents this exact
process and that step that you were
talking about this happened with the ni
the National Institute of Aging they
essentially said that um Alzheimer's and
amalo were synonymous uh through a few
different position papers over time and
so then it came to the point where if
you want wanted to start study outside
of disease you had had to study amalo
that doesn't mean that amalo doesn't
play a role it just means that they they
kind of purposefully ignored um a lot of
other research of of important things
that that are taking part in the process
man just beyond frustrating yeah just
the whatever okay we'll we'll save our
piece on that uh I've got a handful of
really quick questions just to finish us
off here but before we do that a really
fast recap you've you've irritated the
world on at least five
points uh and gave us a lot a lot of
light on if you want to enhance
cognitive function you're good but
you're trying to go to Great you talked
about a lot of different ways to do that
search for novelty in probably vision
and hearing and brain training and and
different things like that and an
important note there is just because
that actual cognitive task is impressive
or complicated doesn't necessarily mean
it's cognitively demanding especially if
you've been doing it a long time right
if whatever that task may be uh if you
are having some sort of deficit brain
fog we'll call it and you called it some
other technical or I'm going to call it
keep call it brain fog right make sure
that you don't have some sort of
holistic Hole uh that is burning
literally burning extra cognitive energy
and so it's not that you have brain fog
per se it's just that you are actually
low on cognitive fuel physically because
of external stressor or sleep or alcohol
like some other micronutrient deficiency
is is most likely
uh at play there right that's that's the
most likely explanation or inflammatory
from long covid like some of process
like that um percussions are not your
brain slamming against your skull wall
and then a lot of strategies stimate
what they actually are and that
explained why those strategies work um
and then that things that like marijuana
and psychedelics not to on them we spent
very little time on those we could
probably discuss that further but
perception is not necessarily the same
as subjective in terms of cognitive
function and I for the other ones you
irritated people with um but we covered
many of them so lastly really fast
because you covered a lot of areas I
tried to do my best to to ask kind of
the quick questions along the way but I
surely missed plenty um so question
number one is if somebody has questions
for you on these things what's the best
way that they can learn more from you
can they contact you directly how does
this work the best place is probably uh
so I have a podcast the best of BR and
fitness podcast uh Josh Turk a
neurologist is is my co-host
neuroscientist and a neurologist working
together so and then we can cover at it
from those relative uh points and so if
it's more clinical he'll cover it if
it's more you know basic science or
statistical or something then I'll come
for I I'll cover it that's a weekly show
or every other week something like that
yeah YouTube and all the normal places
all the normal places and uh so you can
uh it's a question and answer Style Show
so you submit a question and then we'll
answer it one question every episode um
and so that's nice because if you have a
question somebody else probably has that
same question and then other people can
um can benefit from it um and then uh
equally you can my Instagram Dr Tommy
wood uh you can you can DM me but I
might direct you towards the podcast
because then don't DM him just go to the
podcast first um but you also have your
substack as well yeah which is a I love
this format by the way yeah so um it's
free it's free free substack uh best be
Fitness substack when you sign up when
you put in your email uh you get emailed
a PDF which covers all the nutrients and
blood tests that we would recommend just
like basics for for people who worried
about um long-term cognitive function so
all the stuff we talked about today but
they can get that direct PDF to them
that'll be emailed directly to you and
then like every time like we have a news
article or a podcast or whatever that
that comes to the substack okay and
there is an option to pay there they
don't have to though but if they do pay
then they can get access to additional
questions 101 like is that how it works
yeah so we have um there is a an OP you
can always opt to pay for substack
although you don't like all of our
content is free but if you do pay then
we do um we've just started doing some
amas so you can join us on a zoom call
and just ask us where you want literally
live in person live in person wow
craziness yeah I don't know how you do
that you're wild man um and if they want
to come visit your lab at the University
of Washington and get their brain tested
is that uh is that an option yeah uh TBD
TBD coming soon little spoiler friends
there so none yet okay um you've been in
incredibly gracious with your time and
expertise man really appreciate it's
always fun hanging out uh bummer we
didn't get to lift weights this time but
perhaps perhaps next time the last thing
I want to ask you here and I'm putting
you on the spot all right if you got
anointed to the Maha board the make
America healthy again and you said Dr
Tommy wood you are an MD you're a PhD
from Oxford and Cambridge and now the
University of
Washington what would be your first most
important biggest charge you would say
this is what I want to get done to make
America's
brains I don't know if healthier again
is the right word but we'll just say
make them
healthier um I think just because it's
it it would be two-pronged one is
educate people to know that you can slow
and prevent cognitive decline and
improve cognitive function right because
in order to change that you need to know
it's possible and most people don't know
that it's possible and then I would
focus on the importance of cognitive
stimulus and the reason for that is
other aspects supposedly of what's going
to happen in that movement are going to
address metabolic health and other
things that we know are important but
the idea that cognitive function is
driven by cognitive stimulus is still
sort of underappreciated so that would
be that would be my uh my primary
directive and as part of that that I
might dramatically decrease funding for
Mouse studies and Alzheimer's disease
because I don't think that's gone us
anywhere H
interesting and this is from someone who
does animal research in your life I do
that for my job yeah and a lot of what
we do does not relate to humans at all
or doesn't end up relating to humans at
all yeah ends up as a failure so well I
can assure you my friend when your name
comes up on that ballot I will tick that
box and vote for Dr Wood on the thing so
thank you so much man appreciate you
being here thank you so much for having
me this has been really great I hope you
enjoyed that conversation with Dr Tommy
wood to follow along and learn more from
Tommy I encourage you to check out his
social media as well as his free podcast
and substack accounts direct links to
all of those will be provided in our
show notes and I would encourage you to
check them out there thank you for
joining for today's episode my goal as
always is to share exciting scientific
insights that help you perform at your
best if the show resonates with you and
you want to help ensure this information
remains free and accessible to anyone in
the world there are a few ways that you
can support first you can subscribe to
the show on YouTube Spotify and apple
and on Apple and Spotify you can leave
us up to a five-star review subscribing
and leaving a review really does help us
a lot also please check out our sponsors
the show would not exist without them
and they're exceptional products and
services finally you can share today's
episode with a friend who you think
would enjoy it if you have any content
questions or suggestions please put
those in the comments section on YouTube
YouTube I really do try my best to read
them all and to see what you have to say
I use my Instagram and X profiles also
exclusively for scientific communication
so those are great places to follow
along for more learning my handle is Dr
Andy Galpin on both platforms we also
have an email newsletter that distills
all of our episodes in the most
actionable takeaways we have newsletters
on how to improve Fitness in V2 Max how
to build muscle and strength and much
more to subscribe to the newsletter just
go to perform podcast.com and click
newsletter it's completely free and we
do not share your email with anybody
thank you for listening and never forget
in the famous words of Bill Bowerman if
you have a body you are an athlete